<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A scripture-rale to the Lords Table; or, Observations upon M. Humphreys his treatise, intituled, An humble vindication of free admission to the Lords Supper. Tending to discover the loose and prophane principles therein suggested. Published for the undeceiving the weak, and removing offences occasioned by it in the practice of reformation. Being the result of the discourses of some preachers in the county of Gloucester near Stow on the Wold, at their weekly meetings. / Digested by Anthony Palmer pastor of the Church of Christ at Bourton on the Water.</title>
            <author>Palmer, Anthony, 1618?-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1496_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867562</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1496[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A scripture-rale to the Lords Table; or, Observations upon M. Humphreys his treatise, intituled, An humble vindication of free admission to the Lords Supper. Tending to discover the loose and prophane principles therein suggested. Published for the undeceiving the weak, and removing offences occasioned by it in the practice of reformation. Being the result of the discourses of some preachers in the county of Gloucester near Stow on the Wold, at their weekly meetings. / Digested by Anthony Palmer pastor of the Church of Christ at Bourton on the Water.</title>
                  <author>Palmer, Anthony, 1618?-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 182, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for E. Brewster and G. Sawbridge, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible on Ludgate-Hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June. 3.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719. --  Humble vindication of a free admission into the Lords-Supper.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Scripture-Rale TO THE LORDS TABLE; OR, OBSERVATIONS UPON M. <hi>Humphreys</hi> his Treatiſe, Intituled, <hi>An Humble Vindication of Free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the</hi> LORDS SUPPER.</p>
            <p>Tending to diſcover the looſe and prophane Principles therein ſuggeſted.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the undeceiving the weak, and removing offences occaſioned by it in the Practice of Reformation.</p>
            <p>Being the reſult of the Diſcourſes of ſome Preachers in the County of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> near <hi>Stow</hi> on the <hi>Wold,</hi> at their weekly Meetings.</p>
            <p>Digeſted by ANTHONY PALMER Paſter of the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Bourton</hi> on the Water.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tita. 5.22,</hi>
               </bibl> Keep thy ſelf pure.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pro. 24.24.</hi>
               </bibl> He that ſaith to the wicked, Thou art Righteous him ſhall the People curſe.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>E. Brewſter</hi> and <hi>G. Sawbridge,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Bible on Ludgate-Hill, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou haſt peruſed that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Pamphlet of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freys</hi> for <hi>Free Admiſſion,</hi> and taken notice in it of that maſſe of perverting the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by malice or ignorance, or both; of his ſtriking hands with all the ignorant and prophane enemies of Reformation in the Land; Of his much ſelf-condemning So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry, tending to deſtroy all Church-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; Of his carnall and little better then prophane reaſoning; Of his pretendod love to the in bewitching thy conſcience into
<pb facs="tcp:119878:3"/>quietneſſe in ſin, that thy peaceable practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes may help to hold up that ſoul-damning practiſe of mixed communion, and thou ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely receive with wicked perſons, till thy conſcience awake, when the varniſh of his Sophiſtry is worn off; If thou haſt alſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved how the devil and his Agents have diſperſed this Heterodox piece like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſtirred up deluded ſouls to hug it as <hi>Cleopatra</hi> did the Aſpes, or <hi>Uriah</hi> the letter for his own deſtruction; if thou haſt alſo obſerved how many Miniſters through love of <hi>eaſe, intereſt, pride,</hi> and <hi>ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> have <hi>(O thrice horrid wickedneſſe)</hi> been active in ſpreading this abomination among their friends and acquaintance, to the great ſcandall of their holy calling; Thou maiſt think we are not ſharp enough in this our anſwer: But we conſidering that we have been our ſeves ignorant in as plain matters as this, before God of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe enlightned us, and not knowing M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H.</hi> rentations, conſidering leſt we our ſelves ſhould be tempted, and laſtly in hopes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing with him to be earneſt with God for <hi>blotting out his ſin and his Book,</hi> that for the time to come he may do nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, but all for the truth, and the people of God may yet rejoyce in his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb facs="tcp:119878:3"/>as now the ignorant, prophane, formall; and ſuperſtitious do, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to deal with him in a brotherly way.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God we can waſh our hands from the guilt of any prejudice againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H.</hi> perſon, for we know him not, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have heard of any that did; and we can with chearfulneſs ſay, Had not the glory of God, the danger of infection by the ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this erroneous Pamphlet, the experience of the hurt it hath already done, the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all ſuch ſoul-murderers and pleaders for <hi>Baal,</hi> and laſtly, had we not thought it our duty to bear witneſſe againſt this abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, verily we had ſaid nothing, but in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence bewailed M.<hi>H.</hi> and the ſad fruit of his labour againſt the purity of Chriſts wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; What we have done we commit to the hands of the Lord, that he may glorifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by it. And we did the rather in the ſtrength of God adventure to oppoſe the chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the enemies of Reformation in this deplorable Apoſtacy, becauſe the Lord laid it upon our hearts to tremble at that word of his <hi>Eze. 13.22. Becauſe with lies you have made the hearts of the righteous ſad, whom I have not made ſad, and
<pb facs="tcp:119878:4"/>ſtrengthned the hands of the wicked, that he ſhould not return from his wicked way, by promiſing him life, therefore ye ſhall ſee no more vanity, nor divine divinations, for I will deliver my people out of your hand, and ye ſhall know that I am the Lord;</hi> we fear the ſad Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God upon the ſpreaders of this Pamphlet, when Chriſt ſhall come to be revenged on the oppoſers of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>We have but few daies before this our Anſwer want to the Preſſe, ſeen an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Pamphlet by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Drake</hi> (for which we bleſſe God) more ſtrict and acute then ours (intended for our people) which may haply be more ſatisfactory to ſome then ours may ſeem to be; leſt any ſhould ſay We have built upon him or borrowed from him, we can profeſſe we have not borrowed ſo much as a line from him: And truly we can ſay with an honeſt heart unfeigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we long to ſee all the Godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters declare againſt this piece, for we finde, if men of greater parts and much perſpicuity labour not ſuddenly to daſh this idol out of countenance; theſe convictions in ſuch a caſe (where ſo many cry <hi>Great is</hi> Diana) will work in the prophane wits
<pb facs="tcp:119878:4"/>of this Nation <hi>all manner of concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſe,</hi> Rom. <hi>7.8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do not then <hi>Chriſtian Reader,</hi> (out of a vain fear that by this Anſwer thou ſhalt be drawn into ſeparation from the godly) be ſo prejudiced as to forbear to pouder; neither think thou that we intend to be Sciſmaticall in not complying with Godly Miniſters in a work of reall Reformation, according to the Word of God. The thing herd pleaded for in the Preamble, is the neceſſity of Reformation, as the caſe ſtands, to begin with the <hi>minor</hi> part, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily uniting together with their own Miniſter to ſubmit to Diſcipline (the <hi>major</hi> part being deſperately overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ignorance, prophaneneſſe, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, ſtrangers to and forſakers of their Covenant with God in Baptiſm) by conforming with their own mouths their part of the Covenant of God, a thing as our firſt Reformers in the Rubrick before confirmation, as alſo <hi>Calvin, Bucer, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Fulk,</hi> and others affirm to be the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Primitive Church, and may be now much more needfull. This is, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, in ſome of our Pariſhes fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully embraced.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:5"/>
            <p>Reader, We wiſh thee in the Lord to take heed of ſtriking hands with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettors of Free Admiſſion, leſt thy end be worſe then thy beginning, and we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee to him who is able to keep his from partaking with other mens ſinnes and plagues.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July <hi>15. 1653.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:6"/>
            <head>The Authour being abſent from the Preſs deſires the Reader to correct theſe Errata's for him, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle Pag. 3. lin. 13. before <hi>Miniſters</hi> reade <hi>Godly.</hi> In the Book Pag. 1. l. 4. for <hi>import</hi> r. <hi>impart.</hi> p. 4. l. 9. for <hi>obſtructions v. abſtractions.</hi> p. 14. l. 22. for <hi>from</hi> r. <hi>of.</hi> p. 39. l. 14. for <hi>on</hi> r. <hi>in.</hi> p. 72. l. 1. after <hi>eſteem</hi> r. <hi>others.</hi> p. 76. l. 20. for <hi>came</hi> r. <hi>come.</hi> l. 21. for <hi>least</hi> r. <hi>beſt.</hi> p. 81. l. 1. after <hi>expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> r. <hi>unſavoury.</hi> p. 84. l. 10. for <hi>acceptance</hi> r. <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> p. 94. for <hi>their</hi> r. <hi>your.</hi> p. 103. l. 7. for <hi>men</hi> r. <hi>me.</hi> p. 121. l. 17. for <hi>contrive</hi> r. <hi>continue.</hi> p. 156. l. 3. blot out <hi>as.</hi> p. 18. l. 13. for <hi>ſouled</hi> r. <hi>found.</hi> l. 26. after <hi>commit</hi> r. <hi>iniquity.</hi> p. 182. l. 13. for <hi>him</hi> r. <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119878:6"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER to a Book of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MPHREYS,</hi> Entituled, <hi>A free Admiſſion to the Lords Supper.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore we yet enter upon the ſubject it ſelf, give us leave, Reader, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to import unto thee, what hath given us this encouragement, and indeed laid an invincible engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon our ſpirits, as to the bearing witneſs againſt this vile piece.</p>
            <p>We the unworthieſt of the ſervants of Chriſt, having with many others, long waited for the practice of Reformation in the Parochial Congregations of this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119878:7"/>Nation (as the fruit of the prayers, tears and bloud of the Lords people.) And though there have been expedients held forth, yet finding they lay dead upon the ſpirits of too many, it pleaſed the Lord to ſtirre us up, though the laſt and leaſt of our Brethren, to enquire after him in this matter, labouring (as far as we were able) to lay aſide all prejudices and prepoſſeſſions, as to the different wayes were held forth by holy men in the Nation, and ſo to purſue in the Lords ſtrength what he ſhould pleaſe to clear unto us to be his will, and to impreſs upon our hearts, and accordingly to practiſe it: Upon this we betook our ſelves to publick Humiliation in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and Prayer in our reſpective places, as alſo to private weekly ſeeking the Lord together, and conference, in which duties we found the Lord greatly abaſing our ſpirits before him, for the great neglects which had been upon u as to this duty, and we were even afraid to plead with our God, conſidering how greatly we had failed, and put off the work of Reformation from our ſpirits, and the many ſore and great evils the Lord was pleas'd to diſcover
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119878:7"/>upon our hearts, ſpecially that great ſnare (which we deſire with all humility to declare to the praiſe of God, and the admonition of our Brethren) in which we had been long held, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That reforming our Congregations could not be attain'd, but by a Law from the Supream Magiſtrate, thereby exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating our ſelves of the duties the Lord required from us, and the laying the guilt at their door, which the Lord hath now ſhew'd us to be a very ſhift; and we conſider 'tis a great mercy that we have protection from the Magiſtrate in the peaceable practice of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are convine'd and finde that 'tis the power of the Goſpel, the Spirit working by it, that is the only expedient to bring a people to a more cloſe and holy fellowſhip together, by their willing and mutual ſubjection to the rule of the Lord Jeſus over them; We take it to be derogatory from him, for a people to be forc'd by humane power into the full fellowſhip of the Church; ſutable to theſe convincements, we endeavour'd to clear unto our people, the nature of Church-fellowſhip, and the way of it,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119878:8"/>and the neceſſity of Diſcipline, and ſo to call upon them to joyn with us in the Lords work, that we might <hi>give up our ſelves unto him, in a profeſſed ſubjection to the Goſpel, and to grow to a more cloſe fellowſhip together, that all Ordinances might be duly adminiſtred, to the honour of Chriſt, and that formality and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs might be in ſome meaſure broken.</hi> Accordingly an Expedient or Profeſſion was drawn up, wherein we acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our former abominations in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and profeſſing our Repentance before the Lord for them, do ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into, and renew our Covenant with God, that he may be our God, and we his people, to own the Lord Jeſus in his Offices, to ſubmit to godly Order and Diſcipline, to watch over one another, to walk in mutual edification, knit together in love, and ſo receiving others as the Lord ſhall over-power their hearts, ſome account of themſelves being given, and no juſt exception (in a charitable judgement) to be made againſt them; This being the known duty of every compleat member in a particular Church, as in effect granted by both the godly parties, we conceived
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119878:8"/>few or none who were for purity would ſtick at it, the want of which practice we take to be the main reaſon of ſuch great corruptions in the mixt Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which corruptions, we humbly conceive, do put us inevitably upon this practice, if Reformation be <hi>really</hi> effected; That the ſubſtance of this is practiſed by the Presbyterian Brethren, though differing in the expedient, is ſufficiently clear by the practice of the <hi>London</hi> Presbytery, who call upon all, and receive ſuch as freely tender them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and require an account of them, waiting for the coming in of the reſt, which are much the greater party in moſt Pariſhes, without Excommunicating ſuch as refuſe upon what account ſoever, to our beſt information, and ſo the <hi>minor</hi> party do withdraw from the greater, which the corruption of the greater part (in their enmity to Reformation) doth put them and us upon, unleſs we will content our ſelves with the ſetting up a meer form of Diſcipline, but indeed ſit down again on the fame lees of formality, which the Lord hath in ſore judgements ſo much witneſſed againſt, and his ſoul abhorreth. To take the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119878:9"/>boldneſs of a word more, as to our godly Brethren: We humbly conceive, that if that our Principle agreed upon by the moſt of the different wayes (<hi>viz.</hi> That every particular Congregation hath power to reform it ſelf, and ſo Miniſters to be helpfull to each other in it) were <hi>really</hi> practis'd; the controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of Appeals would quickly ceaſe. And further (which is alſo on both hands granted) that an Aſſembly of the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of ſeveral Churches in the Name of Chriſt, is an Ordinance of Chriſt for the healing of differences, the conteſt, Whether this power ſhall be ſtiled <hi>Juri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical</hi> or <hi>Declarative,</hi> and whether this Aſſembly ſhould actually excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate or declare the fact to be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable, would ſurely ceaſe: It is very ſad that a controverſie about Appeals, which happily in well-order'd Churches, may rarely be needfull, ſhould hinder us in the practice of the firſt Principles which all agree in for the ſubſtance of them, and ſhould make us draw harſh conſequences from one anothers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, which both diſavow, and ſo lay ſtumbling blocks in the wayes of the weak, and hinder the hoped ſucceſs of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119878:9"/>the Goſpel and Reformation in the Nation: Let us firſt have our Churches form'd up and order'd according to Goſpel-rules, the ignorant and profane withdrawn from (ſince 'tis clear they cannot be regularly caſt out by Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline) and then the way of thoſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches holding Communion together, would naturally fall in: To this practice (by the good hand of the Lord) we have mutually given up our ſelves, and engaged in the Lord to be helpfull to each other, and to hold Communion together, and a day of ſmall things is wit us, yea we have had very precious teſtimonies of the Lords preſence with it, with ſome of us, for which we bleſs him, and our eyes are upon him to bring his own work to paſs, <hi>who is able to work and none ſhall let it,</hi> Iſa. 43.13.</p>
            <p>The good Lord pardon us, if we are not cleanſed according to the purifying of the Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>We ſhall yet for further ſatisfaction, briefly give an anſwer to the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon objections to, and miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our practice.</p>
            <p>It is enquired in what relation do we conceive our ſelves to ſtand unto the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119878:10"/>reſt, and how doe we eſteem of them?</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the weak (but not obſtinate) that have not ſtrength enough to come up to this practice, we conceive it the Miniſters duty to labour their convince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in publick and private, and the united Brethren to do their duty, by praying for them, and to labour to draw them on to them, by all good wayes and means, and not to neglect them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſuch as <hi>peremptorily</hi> deny to ſubject to Chriſts Diſcipline, upon indeed a profane account, they doe virtually excommunicate themſelves (at leaſt from that particular Church) for being called upon to walk with them in the ſubjection and fellowſhip of the Goſpel, they ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly refuſe ſo to do, but will continue in that looſe eſtate, and though they were baptized, yet by their refuſing to ſubject to Chriſt, they are as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Deficientes à ſuo Baptiſmo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. de diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com.</note> ſuch as for the preſent make void the fruit of their Baptiſm (though if they are after called we do not aſſert a neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing it) and to admit ſuch to the Lords Supper, were, as that acute Author juſtly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119878:10"/>ſaith, and is evident from the Word, to confound and make one the Church of Chriſt and the Kingdom of the devil, as we ſhall (God willing) demonſtrate in this Diſcourſe; and though they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to profeſſe and know God, yet <hi>factis negant foedus Dei,</hi> they deny him and his Covenant in their works and lives,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> and ſo ought not to be admitted to the Seals of it.</p>
            <p>So that ſuch perſons refuſing to own the Covenant of God into which they were tendered in Baptiſm, Jeſus Chriſt in his Offices and Diſcipline, and the fellowſhip of that particular Church, whereof he pretends to be a Member, being called thereunto, or by their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and profaneneſſe not fit to be received; what need any formal act of Excommunication paſſe upon them?</p>
            <p>Specially firſt, Since there was never any ſuch former orderly receiving them into the compleat Communion of the Church upon their <hi>profeſſed faith and obedience before the Church,</hi> nor did ever give their conſents to ſubmit to Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Neither is there any way how they ſhould be rightly excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119878:11"/>for that the <hi>major</hi> part of the Church is corrupt (which we may well ſuppoſe in moſt of the mixt Parothial Congregations in <hi>England</hi>) and ſo will not excommunicate, nor are fit to do ſo, nor fit to chooſe Officers to do it.</p>
            <p>Beſides, as we have formerly hinted, we never heard that either the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian or Congregational Brethren do excommunicate ſuch as ſubmit not; and therefore we rather wonder the more why this ſhould be kept up as a note of difference between them, when practice confutes it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is objected, that we propoſe a <hi>Covenant:</hi> we anſwer for the ſatisfaction of any, that we propoſe the Covenant eſtabliſht in Chriſt Jeſus; The profeſſing to enter into which, we inſiſt upon in order to a perſons partaking the ſeal of it; and thoſe who require profeſſion of repentance and faith in Chriſt before the Presbytery do, in ſubſtance the ſame thing; for Knowledge, Faith, and Obedience are the graces of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is moſt evident that Faith and Repentance in Chriſts and the Apoſtles time were expected and required to be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119878:11"/>profeſſed from the perſon to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis manifeſt that backſliders from this profeſſion were not to be admitted to further Communion, as <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus;</hi> And that thoſe who brake bread, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.42. <hi>continued in the Apostles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and fellowſhip.</hi> It is alſo evident that in the pureſt times the Sacrament of Baptiſm was adminiſtred to the party entring into Covenant, <hi>Credis? Credo, Abrenuncias? Abrenuncio;</hi> Doſt thou beleeve? I beleeve. Doſt thou renounce? I renounce. Plainly, it will then follow, that it is the duty of thoſe who are baptized in Infancy, after they have gladly heard and received the Word, to own, profeſs and enter into the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God into which they were ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in Baptiſm, and to joyn themſelves by a free expreſſed conſent, to the Communion of the Church, that ſo they may <hi>continue</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles doctrine and fellowſhip, and breaking of bread,</hi> &amp;c. This was appointed to be the practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, to require this, and ſo none to be eſteemed in the <hi>compleat Communion</hi> of the Church without it,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119878:12"/>and therefore not to be admitted to the Lords Supper, till ſuch a <hi>covenanting, ſubmitting</hi> and <hi>joyning:</hi> We finde holy <hi>Bucer</hi> much lamenting the want of this practice, in an Epiſtle to <hi>Calvin, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam, ficut iſtud foedus civile, hìc aliquando redintegraſſemus &amp; ſanxiſſemus foedus vitae aeternae, quomodo vos conati ſoli prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiſtis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calvin. <hi>epiſt. fol. p.</hi> 509.</note> Further, <hi>Martyrum Eccleſiae ſevera Diſciplinae religione erant conjunctae &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Speaking further of the Churches there, <hi>Niſi Chriſto Domino ſunt penitus inſiti, ejus quoque Diſciplinam inter ſe reſtituant, de ipſis miſerè metuo;—Non deſunt in omnibus ordinibus, qui reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni ſolidae communionis &amp; Diſciplinae Chriſti adverſantur.</hi> Which we engliſh for the weakeſt, that they may obſerve the concurring judgements of holy men, as to our own practice.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Oh that we had renew'd and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht the Covenant of eternal life, as we have done a civil Covenant. The Churches of the Martyrs were joyned together by the ſevere Religion of Diſcipline. I miſerably fear what may become of our Churches, unleſs they are more cloſely graffed into Chriſt,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119878:12"/>and that they reſtore Diſcipline among themſelves. There are ſome of all orders who are againſt the reſtoring of ſolid fellowſhip and Diſcipline.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now as that which is ſtyl'd a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Covenant, ſo much debated among the godly, we take it to be no more, then ſuch a <hi>mutual agreement</hi> and <hi>joyning</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether mention'd, that <hi>ſolid fellowſhip and Diſcipline may be ſet up,</hi> elſe how can there be an unity and fellow-memberſhip in a particular Church?</p>
            <p>Say ſuch even who diſpute againſt this practice, This is imply'd in the very principles of Chriſtianity; We then apprehend it is not unlawfully but indeed neceſſary, expreſly to profeſs what flows from the principles of it; ſpecially in this caſe, where 'tis a mans own free act that conſtitutes him a member of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church.</p>
            <p>Such a <hi>Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>expreſs conſent</hi> to walk in fellowſhip, and to ſubmit to Diſcipline, we call for; and we believe without it it will hardly be ſet up, unleſs a catechiſtical anſwer or two of a perſon examin'd (though never ſo dead-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and a cloſe enemy to the power of godlineſs) ſhall be thought enough,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119878:13"/>which will be to ſettle again where we were, in old ignorance, lukewarmneſs, looſneſs and formality; in ſtead of ſuch as fear the Lord, walking in fellowſhip with the Father, and one with another in the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now that any that truly fear the Lord ſhould ſtick at this, <hi>viz.</hi> to profeſs to own the Covenant of Gods free grace, to give up themſelves unto it, and to Jeſus Chriſt the Mediatour of it in all his Offices, to walk under his Diſcipline, and in fellowſhip with his people, we cannot but juſtly wonder, and why any godly men of parts ſhould frame and raiſe up bug-bears againſt it; The Lord give them to beleeve, yea to taſte the goodneſs and ſweetneſs of it, and they will be humbled before the Lord that they ever withſtood it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Novelty of this practice, and from keeping any from the Sacrament, is objected to us and others.</p>
            <p>We could anſwer at large here, That it is as old as the Goſpel for beleevers to walk together in fellowſhip in the duties expreſs'd, and for unworthy perſons to be kept from holy things.</p>
            <p>We might moreover produce the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119878:13"/>teſtimony of the moſt eminent Divines, that have been the Lords witneſſes ſince, as the Church of God hath been bleſt with, as <hi>Cyprian, Justin Martyr, Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom, Ambroſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The abundant teſtimonies of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Divines, <hi>Calvin, Beza, Bullinger, Hyperius, Bucer, Zanchy,</hi> &amp;c. with the ſad complaints they make in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the abuſe of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saith <hi>Calvin</hi> in one of his Epiſtles, ſpeaking of the profane, <hi>Sine craſs â Dei injuriâ admitti nequeunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. Epiſt. pag. <hi>438.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quàm turpis &amp; pudenda iſta profanatio Saerorum?</hi> 
               <q>The profane cannot be admitted without groſs injury unto the Lord, How vile and ſhamefull is the profanation of theſe holy things?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Yea ſaith Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> 
               <q>Not onely the want of the Sacraments, but the abuſe of either hazards the weal of the whole Church, yea caſting holy things to dogs, procures a dreadfull doom, as well to <hi>conſenters</hi> as <hi>preſumers,</hi> it being a way to turn the houſe of God into a den of thieves, if profane ones be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Myſteries and Aſſemblies of the faithfull.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119878:14"/>
            <p n="5">5. It is objected, It is tyrannical; We anſwer, we wiſh that people would firſt look to their own duty, <hi>To obey them, that have the rule over them, and to ſubmit themſelves to them,</hi> Heb. 13.17. before they ſo peremptorily aſſert, That the Miniſter doing his duty, in reference to the Lord, and the good of their ſouls, is tyrannical; What tyranny for a Miniſter to make an univerſal invitation to the people he preacheth to, to own the Lord and one another in holineſs and love, and ſo to walk with them? This Objection proceeds from a love of liberty and elbow-room in a carnal courſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Separation is objected; What ſeparation for a Miniſter coming to a people ſetled upon the lees of ignorance and profaneneſs, and having much abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacraments, to call upon all that fear the Lord, to profeſs Chriſt with their mouths, and to give up themſelves to him, and ſo to walk in mutual love and comfort together? Separation from wickedneſs is not ſchiſm, but from the godly; We profeſs to hold Communion with Miniſters and Churches where Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation is in any meaſure practis'd.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119878:14"/>
            <p>Laſtly, A vulgar Objection that is in the mouths of moſt, that we take upon us in this practice to judge the hearts of moſt.</p>
            <p>We anſwer, though we cannot nor do we undertake directly to judge mens hearts, yet we can argue out what is in mens heart, as the Wiſeman ſpeaks, <hi>Counſel in the heart of a man is like deep water, but a man of underſtanding draweth it cut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that firſt, by their <hi>words,</hi> for Chriſt teacheth us ſo to know them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.34. <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh:</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 35. <hi>An evil man out of the evil treaſure of his heart bringeth forth evil things,</hi> as by <hi>lying, ſwearing, hard ſpeeches, bitter ſcoffes,</hi> and <hi>revilings</hi> at ſuch as profeſs godlineſs under the names of Phariſees and hypocrites, with ſuch like corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications, any of which in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice diſcover the heart: How elſe did <hi>Simon Magus</hi> manifeſt himſelf in the gall of bitterneſs?</p>
            <p n="2">2. By their <hi>works, Out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, murders, thefts, falſe witneſs, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> &amp;c. By ſuch fruits we ſhall know them.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119878:15"/>
            <p n="3">3. An <hi>humble Chriſtian</hi> will be willing to have his heart tried, and to have his Miniſter apply rules and evidences to diſcover whether it be ſound and right with the Lord or not?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Where none of theſe fruits doe appear, we do not pretend to make a judgement of mens hearts, ſo there be a willing ſubjection to the Lord and his wayes, to walk in fellowſhip with him and his people.</p>
            <p>Thus have we taken liberty (we truſt without offence to any of the Lords people) with open-heartedneſs and plainneſs, to propoſe what we humbly conceive we have learned of the Lord, and being deeply deſirous to be <hi>aſhamed of our former abominations;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 43.10, 11.</note> we hope we have, or ſhall ſee <hi>the Patern of the Lords houſe;</hi> ſo far as in abundance of mercy, he ſhall pleaſe to uſe us; which the Lord (who will build up and come into his Temple) will in his time reveal to all that love him; In the mean time the Lord give unto us and all our Brethren, whoſe hearts are truly after Reformation to pray more, and diſpute leſs, and laying aſide all animoſities, to do the work of our bleſſed God committed to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119878:15"/>us peaceably, according to the light we have received in our generations.</p>
            <p>Now we ſhall deliver ſome brief and plain obſervations upon this unhappy piece of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys,</hi> aiming at the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the people meerly; conceiving that judicious godly Miniſters are not at all ſtartled in their principles by what he hath vented; And ſo we have laboured to frame ſuch anſwers as are moſt obvious to the people, and not puzzle them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We take notice of this Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis in the Title, viz. <hi>That his Treatiſe was publiſhed for the eaſe, ſupport and ſatisfaction of tender conſciences (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe remedileſſe) in or mixt Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. By <hi>eaſe,</hi> it is plain he means by his Sophiſtry to delude their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings ſo far as that they may without ſcruple partake of the Lords Table with the ignorant and profane; This is to make the conſcience <hi>quiet,</hi> and not <hi>good;</hi> as water cooling a feaver for the preſent, but makes it return with greater vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are confident this hath not <hi>eaſed,</hi> but more <hi>grieved</hi> and <hi>perplexed,</hi> the moſt <hi>tender cohſciences</hi> in the Natton,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119878:16"/>as moſt of the godly bear witneſs, and hath made the hearts of the righteous ſad; The burden of ſuch mixt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating, which hath been and is in the mixt Congregations of <hi>England,</hi> hath been and is the grief and ſad complaint of the ſervants of God both Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and people, and will be proved a ſnare.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whereas he ſaith, <hi>Tender conſciences are otherwiſe remedileſs in our mixt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We offer it to conſideration, Whether he doth not imply that our Congregations ought not to be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo mixt with all manner of profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance, as the moſt are? And whether he doth not propoſe this as ſatisfaction to tender conſciences onely in this exigency of time, when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth no other remedy is to be had for want of a Diſcipline eſtabliſht, and Elder'd Congregations, as he intimates in the cloſe, and as he alloweth of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication all along his book, and ſo his arguments to ſatisfie tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in ſuch an exigency, imply, that other <hi>remedies</hi> are deſirable, and to be lookt after.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119878:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. But we conceive and know, that tender conſciences are not otherwiſe <hi>remedileſs,</hi> if they do not ſubmit to ſuch a mixt Communion, we apprehend <hi>the remedy</hi> laid down in the Preamble to be <hi>proper</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> and what others are pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd by godly men in the Nation: Surely this evil is not ſo <hi>remedileſs,</hi> if godly Miniſters and people will do their duty. We deſire with all ſubmiſſion to remark, that many do hotly diſpute againſt <hi>Erastianiſm,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Of Church-power being in the Magistrate,</hi> and yet they ſay Diſcipline cannot be practiſed without a Law from them (though they will protect men peaceably doing their duty) which we look upon as a very ſnare upon the ſpirits of good men. Therefore (bleſſed be God) there are comfortable remedies, if applied, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wallowing back again into that ſea of dead bloud, that corrupt, carnal, dead-hearted, formal, prophane, ignorant practice of worſhip we have been in.</p>
            <p>We cannot but likewiſe take notice of an expreſſion in the Epiſtle to the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as it ſeems penn'd by another, wherein he cals this practice of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admiſſion, <hi>precious light;</hi> We are ſure
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119878:17"/>it hath by the holy people of this and other Nations, been ever accounted <hi>groſs darkneſs,</hi> born witneſs againſt by moſt of the Confeſſions and Martyrs in all ages of the Church, yea hiſt at as a <hi>profane principle,</hi> and hath ſent many of as eminent Saints as ever this Nation was bleſt with, to priſons and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Oh horrid! that the liberty of all ungodly perſons, promiſcuouſly to profane the holy things of God, ſhould now be ſtiled <hi>precious light!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to take notice and examine how <hi>precious</hi> it is, yet with all due reſpect to the Author.</p>
            <p>His Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.27. <hi>They all drank of it: All the twelve without exception; from whence,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I gather free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. But we are bold to ſay moſt inconſequently, as ever was Argument drawn by a man of parts. Juſt the contrary will be thus argued, There were but only twelve Apoſtles (though Chriſt had many other followers and hearers) admitted by Chriſt to his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, therefore all of all ſorts were not admitted to come; this is ſure more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourably argued.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119878:17"/>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe onely twelve Apoſtles, none being under ſcandal or ignorance, brake bread with Chriſt, therefore <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, ſwearers, liars, drunkards, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean perſons, covetous, revilers and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of godly Preachers and people,</hi> ſuch as moſt Congregations, to ſpeak out, do abound with, may now come to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion of Saints.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Here is the force of his Argument, Chriſt took twelve with him, and all thoſe twelve drank of the Cup, therefore all might have come that would. Twelve Aldermen are invited by a Major to a feaſt, and becauſe <hi>all</hi> the twelve eat, therefore all the beggars of the Town might have come.</p>
            <p>If the ſtreſs of his Argument lie in <hi>Judas</hi> his partaking of it, he might have been pleas'd ſo to have urg'd it, and not put ſuch a fallacy upon weak people:</p>
            <p>And if it do, we anſwer briefly here, (and more fully where he plainly ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth it) that it was irrational <hi>Judas</hi> ſhould have been kept off before he had committed the ſcandal, ſpecially Chriſt acting in that as an ordinary Miniſter and Paſt our to his Church.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119878:18"/>
            <p>In his ſtating the Queſtion, he aſſerts, <hi>All in the viſible Church are capable of all Ordinances, but Infants, diſtracted perſons, and excommunicated perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let the Reader obſerve, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> allows Excommunication: of whom? of ſuch as are detected for ſcandal, or unduly admitted into the Church formerly, being groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; How will free Admiſſion and Excommunication ſtand together? If it be every mans duty to come, why ſhould any hinder him?</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, <hi>unleſs excommunicated:</hi> But what if they are <hi>excommunicable?</hi> Doth not that Paſtour and Church ſinne before the Lord if they do not excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate them? If the greater part be ſuch, ought not the Paſtour and ſuch as fear God with him (due means having been uſed for the conviction of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſuperſtitious and ſcandalous) to withdraw from them, in the exerciſe of this Ordinance, if Diſcipline cannot otherwiſe be taken up, as in a corrupt majority how can it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. ſaith he, <hi>Though he queſtions the capacity of many people, becauſe a ſolemn preparation is required, yet he ſaith,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119878:18"/>he humbly perſwades himſelf that for the Ministers and Churches part as to offering Chriſt freely, there is ſuch an univerſal capacity, that if any come in profeſſing themſelves ready to enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Chriſt, and ſerve him in this Ordinance, we may encourage him, from Rev.</hi> 22.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is the fallacy couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that runnes thorow the whole Book.</p>
            <p>But is not this a ſad confounding of things?</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is moſt true, that ſinners are freely to be invited to Chriſt? But muſt it be preſently to this Ordinance of the Supper? If they do indeed profeſs themſelves ready to enter into Covenant with Chriſt, and their lives do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict this covenanting, the Church is to receive them, but ought not this to be an <hi>explicit</hi> profeſſion to the Church or Officers of it? Muſt a profane perſon ruſhing upon the ordinance as formerly, be ſuppoſed to do ſo, <hi>meerly</hi> becauſe he comes? Upon this ſcore, who ever they be, Turks, Pagans, Jews, if they hear a Sermon, and come and eat and drink at the Supper, it is to be ſuppoſed they do
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119878:19"/>implicitely enter into Covenant with Chriſt; how abſurd would this be, and makes the bloud of the Covenant an unclean thing?</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, <hi>his humble perſwaſion</hi> is not argument enough to prove, that the Miniſter and Church is to be ſo <hi>remiſs</hi> and <hi>ſlight</hi> in this matter, without a former profeſſion before the Lord and the Church, of every perſons willingneſs to covenant with Chriſt, and ſubmit to Diſcipline, (eſpecially in this lapſed ſtate we now are in) and the Church in a judgement of charity ſatisfied in them; if he means ſuch a precedent, explicite, open profeſſion of every perſon, we agree with him; but unleſs his Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation be the Phoenix of all in <hi>England,</hi> I beleeve he would have but a few Communicants upon ſuch an account, as trial hath been made by many godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in this particular.</p>
            <p>But as we have ſaid, if he mean his meer coming, is ſuch a profeſſion, we take it to be very deluſory, indeed a very mocking of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Beſides M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> well knows how unduly all ſorts have been admitted to the Communion of the Church former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119878:19"/>and therefore now in times of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation the caſe is diſtant; how few, alas to be found that know or have been ever truly taught what it is to covenant with Chriſt?</p>
            <p>This ſtrange latitude that this latter ſenſe implies, is farre from the Churches ſtrictneſs in the pureſt times, in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting their <hi>Catechumeni</hi> into the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Church.</p>
            <p>He goes on, <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. <hi>That he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves none unleſs excommunicated</hi> (ipſo jure, <hi>or</hi> facto) <hi>ought to be refuſed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he means by <hi>excommunicated, ipſo jure,</hi> ſuch as of <hi>right</hi> ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the Church, then the matter is ended; for it is moſt true, that none but ſuch as are already excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated, are to be kept from the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſuch without queſtion ought to be kept off, and if ſo, he grants what we deſire.</p>
            <p>But let us examine his further <hi>proofs</hi> for <hi>free Admiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His firſt Scripture is from <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>There was free admiſſion to the Paſſeover, therefore to the Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119878:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If all came to the Paſſeover, then there was no Excommunication in the Jewiſh Church, which Scripture <hi>Eraſtus</hi> and his followers uſe to prove there was none; And by this argument he will make void Excommunication now, (which as he hath ſtated the matter, will not be well conſiſtent with his free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.) All to come to the Lords Supper, as all did come to the Paſſeover, none kept back from the one, therefore none from the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But we deny that all were admitted to the Paſſeover; he confeſſeth himſelf, from <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. that they were to be kept off for a moneth, for legal polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which was a type of ſinne) ſuppoſing that they ſhould cleanſe themſelves in that moneth, otherwiſe they were longer to be kept off, as will neceſſarily follow, the end of their keeping off for that time, being that they ſhould be cleanſed, as <hi>Pareus,</hi> and others upon the place well obſerve.</p>
            <p>We cannot here inſiſt to enforce the many Scriptures and Arguments which have been brought by others, to prove that the Jews were kept from the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over both for legal and moral unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119878:20"/>for ſcandalous ſins, which we are confident neither he nor all the world will be able to anſwer: Therefore we do indeed the more wonder that he will urge this, and go about to impoſe it on Miniſters and people, ſo ſlightly paſſing over what ſo many learned and godly men have wrote, ſpecially the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters, and <hi>Scotch</hi> Divines, and not take notice of their weighty argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>But we will clear it from the Scriptures plainly. See, <hi>Reader,</hi> Numb. 15.30, 31. &amp; Chap. 19. <hi>That there was a cutting off from the Congregation ſuch as did ought preſumptuouſly againſt the Lord, that deſpiſed the word of the Lord, that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Sabbath.</hi> So <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.8. <hi>Whoſoever would not come to build the Temple within the three dayes, ſhould be ſeparated from the Congregation.</hi> And <hi>whoſoever ſhould confeſs Chriſt was to be put out of the Synagogue,</hi> John 9.22. Yea himſelf grants, that the Jews had their ſeveral degrees of Excommunication, <hi>p.</hi> 84. of his Book. And is not the neglect of keeping of the profane from the holy things charg'd upon the Prieſts as a great evil? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. <hi>Her Prieſts have
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119878:21"/>violated my Law, and have profaned my holy things, they have put no difference between the holy and profane,</hi> &amp;c. Yea further, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44 7, 9. <hi>The uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in heart were not to enter into the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary to pollute it,</hi> that is, ſuch as did manifeſtly in their lives appear to be ſo, though they had received outward Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion. And the Lord ſaith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>That ſuch of the Prieſts that thus tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Covenant of the Lord ſhould bear their iniquity, and they ſhould not come near unto him to do the Office of a Prieſt any more.</hi> This alſo is typical of the ſpiritual Sanctuary the Church of Chriſt in Goſpel times.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, it will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily appear, without troubling the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with any more, that the Jews were kept off from the Paſſeover for preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous and ſcandalous ſins; for if they were cut off from the Congregation, then they came not at the Paſſeover; and one end of their cutting off was, that they might not defile the Paſſeover, as hath been proved; Therefore, Reader, thus farre it appears M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> hath deluded thee.</p>
            <p>His next Scripture is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.7. <hi>We
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119878:21"/>being many are all partakers of one bread, All at Corinth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, All ſuch who <hi>joyned themſelves</hi> to the Church by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Apoſtles did ſo, who came and profeſſed ſubjection to the Lord Chriſt and his Goſpel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. and <hi>became a chaſte Spouſe unto Chriſt,</hi> Chap. 11.2. theſe did all partake it. But, Sir, were the Parochial Churches in <hi>England</hi> (though we deny them not to be Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in a large ſenſe) ſo brought in? Will you compare the obſtinate igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of this age of people, to <hi>profeſſing Saints at Corinth?</hi> whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſtyleth, <hi>Called to be Saints, and ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2. as we ſhall elſwhere urge.</p>
            <p>Are not zealous Preachers of the Goſpel, upon laying aſide corrupt forms, and ſuperſtitious uſages in too many places, deſpiſed and reviled by the moſt, as Novelliſts and Troublers of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> would, do you imagine, <hi>Paul</hi> write to ſuch as Saints and ſanctified, and ſtile the Churches the chaſte Spouſes of Chriſt, where ſo much abetted profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and affected ignorance?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides the Apoſtles drift in that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119878:22"/>place is not to prove that <hi>all</hi> did partake of the bread, but that thoſe that <hi>did</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, were <hi>one bread</hi> together, and therefore they ſhould flie idolatrous ſeaſts, leſt they were made <hi>one body</hi> with them, by eating with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. But faith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys, Many of theſe Corinths were ready to go to their Idols, and to commit Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw,</hi> It ſeems then they were but <hi>ready</hi> to go to their Idols, they did not <hi>actually</hi> commit Idolatry. The truth is this, ſome of them through weakneſs, did eat at their feaſts, of meats ſacrificed to Idols, which things the Apoſtle ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely warns them of, leſt they ſhould be tempted back to Idolatry, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Jews, and the Lords judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them; not as if theſe <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths</hi> did already commit Idolatry, but he warns them againſt it, and ſo in the cloſe of the Chapter ſtates the eating of thoſe meats, in it ſelf an indifferent action, ſo the ſnare to Idolatry be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and offence to the weak brother; which Interpretation is given by all ſound Interpreters we meet with.</p>
            <p>Now to ſtile the <hi>Corinths</hi> lukewarm Chriſtians. as indifferent to Chriſtianity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119878:22"/>or Idolatry, and ſo to juſtifie the Admiſſion of ſuch to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is more then this Scripture will allow.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By this Argument alſo he would prove, that ſuch as are actual Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters may be admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is free Admiſſion to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>But 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. ſeems to him to ſtrike further, <hi>Theſe Corinths were mutinous and drunken at the Supper, for this they were reproved and directed to examine themſelves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but for their coming 'twas their duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Theſe <hi>Corinths</hi> being newly come out of Idolatry, as hath been ſhew'd, did in imitation of the idolatrous ſeaſts keep their <hi>love feaſts,</hi> Jude ver. 12. when they came to the Lords Supper. At which feaſt there was exceſs among them, not preciſely at the Lords Supper, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. of that Chapter, where it is ſaid, <hi>Every one took his own Supper, and ſo ſome were drunk,</hi> that is, ſome were exceſſively feaſted and filled, while others, the poorer ſort, wanted: This diſorder the Apoſtle reproves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifies their practice; but ſurely never
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119878:23"/>thought any Miniſter of the Goſpel would plead this for an allowance, that profane drunkards ought to come to the Lords Table.</p>
            <p>Reader obſerve, that by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in perverting theſe Scriptures, he pleads for impenitent Idolaters and drunkards to come to the Sacrament; Hath not this man a great care of the the Lords worſhip?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It doth not appear, that this was an obſtinate, conſtant practice of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths,</hi> but a <hi>weakneſs,</hi> they being newly come out of their Heatheniſm.</p>
            <p>Now ſaith he, <hi>For their coming no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſaid againſt it, that was their duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Upon this diſtinction we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Author took up this judgment; we ſhall further ſpeak to it, where he more at large urgeth it.</p>
            <p>For preſent, we deny there is any <hi>abſolute</hi> command of coming to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, unleſs ſo qualified, as the word of God requires; <hi>worthineſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very formality of their coming. There's a double <hi>worthineſs, Real,</hi> the ſanctification of the perſon, without this no particular perſon ought to come
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119878:23"/>(at leaſt begun upon him) <hi>for he eats and drinks damnation without it; And let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat, ſo,</hi> and not otherwiſe, without his exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination he ought not to come; this as to his own conſcience.</p>
            <p>Will not M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> preach thus, Unleſs you examine your <hi>ſelves,</hi> that is, as to your repentance and faith, you ought not to come to this holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? Or will he ſay thus, Though you do not, yet you ought to come, that's your duty? For, ſaith the Author, <hi>Nothing is or could be ſaid againſt their coming:</hi> Nothing?<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.27, 29, 30.</note> Is <hi>eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing judgement to themſelves</hi> nothing? Be <hi>ſtricken with ſickneſs, weakneſs, death,</hi> Is this nothing? But he will ſay, This was for their unworthineſs; therefore they ought not to come, being under ſuch unworthineſs. If a Maſter enjoyn his ſervant not to come into his preſence, unleſs ſo and ſo habited upon pain of death; ſhall that perſon yet go, becauſe he will ſay, he ought to go to his Maſter, 'tis his duty? So ſaith the Lord Chriſt by <hi>Paul,</hi> He that comes to me in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of my laſt Supper, ought to come with ſuch and ſuch a worthineſs, or he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119878:24"/>incurs death and judgement without his repentance: Now will that perſon ſay, or will any ſay to him, 'Tis your duty however to come? Nay, Is it not their duty to abſtain? 'Tis his duty indeed to examine and prepare himſelf, and ſo to come, but 'tis not his duty to come, if unworthineſs be upon him: 'Tis true, there is an indefinite mediate obligation of all fleſh to obey God the Creatour in every command of his, and 'tis their ſinne and condemnation in failing, but there are ſome duties of his worſhip, wherein he hath appointed that his Name ſhall be thus and thus ſanctified by his own people, and to approach him in theſe without it, is a greater ſin then to abſtain from them, eſpecially in this Ordinance. So much for real worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, There is <hi>viſible worthineſs.</hi> in reference to the Church; and this the Church is to look to, in order to the right honouring of the name of God in his worſhip, and its own purity. Now <hi>Paul</hi> in this Chapter doth only admoniſh the <hi>Corinths,</hi> and convince them, and ſo ſeems to hope their amendment in the two laſt verſes of the Chapter, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119878:24"/>though he doth not give order to the Church here to excommunicate them, which 'tis not probable he ſhould before <hi>reproof</hi> and <hi>admonition</hi> (eſpecially being newly brought over to the faith of the Goſpel, and ſo but tender) yet no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion if they had continued in this ſinne, as the people in the mixt Congregations do in theirs, the Church ſhould have had direction about it, as well as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inceſtuous perſon, and others in the fifth Chapter; for he will grant theſe to be ſcandalous ſins in the Church, and if perſiſted in to merit Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. That theſe corruptions ſo witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt by ſuch <hi>ſevere reproofs</hi> and <hi>judgements</hi> from heaven ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as paterns of practice, is moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, eſpecially comparing the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> &amp; our Parochial Churches, and ſo to draw a parallel practice, ſtiled <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, the chaſte Spouſe of Chriſt, converted by the preaching of Paul,</hi> a Church ſtored with rare <hi>ſpiritual gifts,</hi> and ours for the moſt part trained up under a dead form of worſhip, and a little heartleſs preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (for a great part, to ſpeak plainly againſt the power of godlineſs, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119878:25"/>ſuch as do profeſs it) in ignorance of the way of life and righteouſneſs by the Lord Jeſus, living in known, groſs, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſins, as hath been ſhewed, and which cannot but be evident to the Author we deal with.</p>
            <p>To proceed, The <hi>Achillean</hi> place is the next in the ſame page 7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. as if it were a new Diſcovery, when long ſince urged by <hi>Eraſtus</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, the vanity of the Inference hath been over and over confuted by many godly men, which he is pleaſed to paſſe by. <hi>Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>here is a clear Scripture for free Admiſſion; The Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites that paſſed thorow the ſea and wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs were baptized under the cloud, and drank of the ſame ſpiritual rock,</hi> that is, <hi>admitted freely to both Sacraments, all ſcandalous ones without exception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Sir, Why do you not ſpeak out, but here and there mince in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication? When you plead for all ſcandalous perſons to be admitted, and by conſequence <hi>received</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued</hi> in the Church: If the ſcope of all you aſſert be in want of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> why do you go about to prove it an <hi>abſolute</hi> duty?</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119878:25"/>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider the ſcope of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, which is, firſt, to warn the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths</hi> of eating with Idolaters, as hath been opened, leſt they ſhould be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted back, and ſo fall into the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the Jews, who were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized, drank of the ſame ſpiritual rock, ate manna, and yet for their ſins, the wrath of God came afterwards upon them: alſo in the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe it is ſaid, <hi>With many of thoſe God was not well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed,</hi> which may be underſtood for their evil eating and drinking, as well as the reſt of their ſins, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Trap</hi> on his Notes on the place.</p>
            <p>Now if we ſhould allow the parallel of theſe types, which <hi>Beza</hi> will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low to <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> it will not in the leaſt meaſure prove his deſign: For firſt, the manna and the water of the rock were their <hi>ordinary food,</hi> though they had alſo Evangelical ſignifications; ſo that if ſcandalous ſinners had been debarred of theſe, they had been debarred of their ordinary food, which makes a vaſt difference between their caſe in the wilderneſſe, and ours at the Lords Table.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſuch ſins as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119878:26"/>were committed <hi>after</hi> the eating of the manna, and drinking the water of the rock, for as ſoon as they fell to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and whoredoms the wrath of God came upon them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 26.64, 65. therefore they did not eat of the manna, and drink of the rock after the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe ſins: Alſo theſe ſcandalous ſinners were to be caſt off by death by the Law, except ſuch of them as did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſo not to be admitted: Hence we have this Argument from this place againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys,</hi> as given forth by learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gilleſpy in his Aarons Rod, viz.</hi> If God himſelf did execute ſuch Diſcipline upon thoſe who were tainted with Idolatry, fornication, and other groſs ſins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that he would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to enjoy their former liberty of eating of the manna, and drinking of that rock (as typifying Chriſt) untill they mourned, repented, confeſſed, and atonement was made for them; it is much leſs the will of God that ſuch ſcandalous ſinners as are impenitent, and manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly irreconciled to God, ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and received to the Lords Supper. But the former is true, Therefore the latter. If he urge here, They ought to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119878:26"/>be put back by Excommunication, why doth he ſo poſitively and peremptorily urge this Text to prove free Admiſſion, when indeed the ſcope of the Apoſtle is to prove the contrary, and to warn them of it, leſt the ſame judgments come upon them alſo?</p>
            <p>It is ſad to bring that for an example of allowance (let him have what ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions he pleaſe) which is left as an example of the fearfull judgement of God to be trembled at in all ſucceeding ages by all abuſers of Church-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
            <p>His next Scripture is, <hi>The Parable in Marth.</hi> 22. <hi>compared with Luke</hi> 14.16, 23. <hi>that all were invited to the feaſt, and the ſervants brought in all both good and bad; whence he infers free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We do not finde any ſolid Divines underſtanding this feaſt of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor is there the leaſt colour ſo to do: But this Parable is to ſet forth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The tender of the Goſpel to the Jews, who refuſing it, it is ſent to the Gentiles, expreſſed by the high-wayes and hedges, the remote corners of the world; So that the calling of all in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119878:27"/>
               <hi>Luke</hi> is the call of the Goſpel for all to come in and accept of the terms of it; And all that come and profeſs ſubjection to it are received by the Church, and ſo to partake of all the Goſpel-Ordinances till by their converſations they ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves hypocrites.</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, <hi>In Matthew, The ſervants of the Maſter of the feaſt, brought in good and bad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer hereunto, Firſt, All both good and bad are invited freely by the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Good and bad are gathered in, but by the bad is certainly meant cloſe hypocrites, for when they come in, they pretend ſubjection to the Goſpel, and ſo are put under Goſpel-adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: But Chriſt ſhews the danger of that hypocriſie, and that if ſuch as come unto the feaſt of the Goſpel in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie not having the wedding garment, the regeneration of the Spirit upon them, ſhall be caſt into utter darkneſs; That this is the plain ſcope of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is the aſſent of moſt godly Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters.</p>
            <p>Now that hypocrites ſhall be in the Church till the later day, who queſtions?
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119878:27"/>But that when their hypocriſie is viſible, they ſhall be caſt out of the Church, and ſo not admitted to the Communion of the Church in the Supper, is clear from the Diſcipline Chriſt hath elſwhere inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. and by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> own conceſſion in allowing the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Excommunication; and though the perſon without the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (repreſenting all the cloſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites) was firſt admitted by the ſervants, yet he was not admitted as not having a <hi>wedding garment,</hi> but ſuppoſed in a judgement of charity to have it, becauſe he profeſſeth to put on Chriſt in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting to him, but that he is therefore to be continued and admitted to all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances upon his ſcandal appearing, as we have ſaid, cannot in the leaſt meaſure be gathered from this Parable: But we need ſay no more, but that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> hath perniciouſly perverted the ſcope of the Parable, Jews and Gentiles muſt be called to faith in Chriſt by the Miniſtry, Therefore ignorant and prophane muſt be admitted to the Lords Supper; it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>This perſon was compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to come in</hi> (ſtill underſtanding it of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119878:28"/>the Sacrament, which is we conceive confuted) <hi>which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>was his duty, and he had no minde to come in, if he could have helpt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> If he would not have come in if he could have helpt it, &amp; ſo was compelled, what is this but a forcible compelling of men to the Sacrament? Sure here's liberty and free Admiſſion deſtroyed again, but by a worſe principle, <hi>viz.</hi> that people may be compell'd to the Sacrament, though they have no minde to come; for what elſe can be gather'd from that expreſſion? If he then do ſo underſtand it of a forcible compelling to the Sacrament againſt mens wils, we referre him for an anſwer to all ſolid Proteſtant Divines againſt the Papiſts, urging this Scripture for forcible compelling to ſubject to the Church, and ſo to make Churches by the ſword; And likewiſe to what hath been anſwer'd to the practice of the Prelates in puniſhing perſons if they came not once a year to the Sacrament, which is now hiſt at by all the godly in the Nation, as a practice moſt abominable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to come was not his ſinne</hi> (ſtill unduly meaning the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119878:28"/>
               <hi>but without his wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath been anſwered, that to come is not his duty unleſs he hath his wedding garment; 'tis his greater ſinne to come ſo, then to refrain, becauſe 'tis an abominable mocking of the Lord, who hath laid upon men no abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to come, but a conditional, therefore not to come according to the conditional command is the ſin.</p>
            <p>By this compelling therefore is meant the <hi>free invitations</hi> and <hi>compellations</hi> of the Goſpel (<hi>Evangelii inculcatione &amp; hortationum inſtantiâ,</hi> as <hi>Bucer</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.) upon which the Gentiles ſhall come into it, and not of compelling men againſt their wils to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a practice the ſoul of the Lord abhors.</p>
            <p>His fourth Obſervation, <hi>Pag.</hi> 10. <hi>That our Saviour explains his own Parable, Many are called, few are choſen; That is, ſaith he, the work of the Ministry, we are freely to offer Christ in his Ordinances; but few are choſen, that is the work of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Very true, many are outwardly called by the Goſpel, but few choſen,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119878:29"/>'tis only known to the Lord who are his choſen ones, and therefore the Church looks to <hi>outward profeſſion</hi> and <hi>calling,</hi> but if any deny their <hi>call,</hi> by <hi>contrary walking</hi> to it, nothing is here gathered to the contrary, but the Church muſt caſt them out; Secret election belongs to God, but the electing of ſitly qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons to the Lords Supper, belongs to the Church; It is the work of the Miniſters to <hi>offer Christ freely in the Ordinances,</hi> but in <hi>Chriſts own way</hi> and <hi>method,</hi> to offer him <hi>firſt</hi> in the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ordinance, and if any ſoul <hi>profeſs</hi> to embrace him before the Lord and the Church, then to have the ſeal of his love in the Supper, which things indeed he doth <hi>confound</hi> and <hi>mix</hi> all the way, and which being diſcovered the ſnare is broken.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That few are choſen, that is the work of God, yea that the ſervant brought in the man, it was the Lord only took upon him to judge and caſt him out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who doubts this, but it is the Lords work to chooſe? The Church meddles not with mens <hi>election,</hi> but their <hi>calling</hi> and <hi>profeſſion;</hi> it is <hi>his</hi> work to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119878:29"/>caſt out, his <hi>work alone</hi> to diſcover cloſe hypocrites at the laſt day; But, <hi>Sir,</hi> we beſeech you, Is this <hi>excluſive</hi> of all other <hi>caſting out</hi> by the Church, why then do you ſpeak of Excommunication? Your indeed continued contradiction: Is not the Church to caſt out open ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons, or to withdraw from ſuch as ſcorn at Diſcipline, or have been unduly admitted as compleat members into the Church, being groſly ignorant? ſurely you will grant both.</p>
            <p>He concludes this Argument as with a victory from <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42. <hi>Who is that faithfull ſteward that gives the houſhold their portion in due ſeaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We anſwer (and may we do it with grief of heart) not ſuch as give their Maſters bread to dogs, his enemies in their wicked lives; or ſuch as refuſe to <hi>profeſs ſubmiſſion</hi> and <hi>ſubjection</hi> to him, being called thereunto; He is a <hi>faithfull ſteward</hi> who <hi>caſts</hi> out his maſters traiter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enemies, who diſhonour his <hi>family,</hi> and gives his <hi>bread,</hi> the <hi>ſeal</hi> of his love, to his <hi>houſhold</hi> onely; A ſtronger Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument needed not be brought againſt him.</p>
            <p>The Lord forbid the godly Miniſters
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119878:30"/>of this Nation ſhould now, after all their crying for Reformation be found ſuch Stewards as <hi>free Admiſſion</hi> would have them.</p>
            <p>What he urgeth from <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. is as impertinent, where <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus, to take heed, and to feed the Church of God,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.22. &amp; 4.16.</note> That Church which is deſcribed to be <hi>built up as an habitation of God thorow the Spirit,</hi> fitly framed and compacted together, as brought into the order of the Goſpel, by the holy and powerfull preaching of it by the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Now, 1. What's this to ignorant, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, carnal, formal, profane, ſuperſtitious and malicious Congregations, that they muſt ſtill be fed with this Ordinance, to the flattering of them in a miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtate, and ſend them with a cruel pity to hell with them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such are not fit to be <hi>fed</hi> with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, which have not <hi>feeding</hi> ſouls for it.</p>
            <p>His next place is, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.5. &amp; <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. where he ſaith, <hi>John baptizeth all that come unto him for Baptiſm, though he cals them vipers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This he cals a ſtrong place; But,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119878:30"/>Reader, ſee the weakneſs of it for his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is queſtioned by many learned men, Whether theſe Phariſees were baptized by <hi>John;</hi> but if we grant they were, we anſwer,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Phariſees came to <hi>Johns</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, <hi>John</hi> ſeeing them, deals roundly with them, and cals them a generation of vipers, and pleads with them, <hi>Who had warned them to flie from the wrath to come?</hi> ſeeing they were ſelf-righteous perſons, and need no repentance in their own conceits; His Baptiſm was the Baptiſm of repentance, and ſinners, loſt ſinners, who ſaw their need of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance came to it; What made they in the number of them? Thus <hi>John</hi> labours to convince them; now ſuch of them as were wrought upon, and came to him, caſting off their own former ſelf-conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and <hi>confeſſing their ſins,</hi> and ſo ſubmitting to the Baptiſm of repentance and remiſſion of ſins, were baptized of him, as 'tis clear <hi>Mark</hi> 1.5. <hi>They were baptized of him, confeſſing their ſins;</hi> ſo that 'tis not to be underſtood that <hi>John</hi> lookt upon thoſe as continuing in their Phariſaiſm, and ſo a <hi>generation of vipers,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119878:31"/>when he baptizeth them; but as repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinners, and ſo preſſeth them to bring forth <hi>fruits worthy of repentance;</hi> Now who denieth ſuch perſons ſo confeſſing their ſins generally before the Preachers and Church, and ſo defiring to be received into the fellowſhip of the Church, and the priviledge of all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but that they ought to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? What is this to ſuch who either were never called upon ſo to profeſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and faith, or being ſo called upon, do yet ſcornfully refuſe to do it? as it is too evident where ever Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation hath been ſet on foot in this Nation.</p>
            <p>He makes ſuch another inſtance in that of <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. <hi>Where</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they immediately communicate with them, diſtributing freely, not only the Word, but Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what were theſe? Such as at the Apoſtles preaching were <hi>pricked at the heart,</hi> crying out in deep conviction of conſcience, <hi>Men and brethren, what ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> and profeſſing openly their repentance.</p>
            <p>What is this again, to ſuch whoſe hearts riſe up againſt the Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119878:31"/>who cry up a Service-book above Goſpel-preaching, full of obſtinate ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance? The Author knows he need not go farre to finde ſuch; which are thoſe godly men ſtick at as to Admiſſion to the Lords Supper, and not poor, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, repenting ſouls, who profeſs it before the Lord and his people.</p>
            <p>His next Scripture is <hi>Acts</hi> 10.28. which he cals a peculiar place; <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Was very ſcrupulous of admitting Chriſtian Communion With any but the Jews, it being held pollution under the Law to partieipate in any thing with the Gentiles, but after the viſion God inſtructed him to call no man unclean.</hi> Reader, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this,</p>
            <p>Becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> had a viſion that the Goſpel was to come to the Gentiles, and therefore he might have converſt with them, therefore every Gentile, every leud, ignorant, profane perſon, is to be accounted ſo elean, as to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Lords Supper: For this is the whole force of the Argument: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man knows that by that viſion no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe is meant but the preaching of the Goſpel to the Gentiles; ſure conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate unprejudiced perſons will not be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119878:32"/>heightned againſt Reformation by ſuch kinde of reaſoning, when the nakedneſs of it is diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Now, ſaith he further, <hi>I have learned to count no man unclean unleſs excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No? What if half or more of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation be actually unclean perſons, living in known ſins, and the Miniſter and the reſt do not excommunicate or withdraw from them, Doth not ſin lye upon them for the neglect of their duty? And are not ſuch perſons to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as unclean by them? Many do finde a ſhift for conſcience this way; It had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed more colour, if the people had profeſſed a willing ſubjection to Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline before, and Excommunication had been ever duly adminiſtred in the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Churches of <hi>England,</hi> but it will not be <hi>à ſalvo</hi> in the corruptions they now lie under.</p>
            <p>To theſe he adds the texts which ſet forth free grace, and ſo pleads; <hi>When the Goſpel freely offers Chriſt, when Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers himſelf and grace, which are the things ſignified, How can any have the conſcience to turn them away from the ſigns?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119878:32"/>
            <p>This is a very confounding of things, and indeed a meer fallacy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Doth not Chriſt freely offer himſelf to Jews, Turks and Pagans, therefore have you ſo eaſie a conſcience as to give them the Seals before they profeſs to receive the grace offered unto them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is true, when Chriſt offers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and grace, and ſo ſouls <hi>receive</hi> him, and <hi>profeſs</hi> to do ſo, when they have (in the charitable judgement of the Church) the ſubſtance, none ought to deny them the Signs; but when they refuſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare or profeſs this, and have all their dayes abuſed this Ordinance through groſs ignorance and profaneneſſe, who can have ſo pitileſs a conſcience as to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to continue to do ſo, when they doe not their duty to prevent it? The Lord lay it not to the charge of any, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we come to his Reaſons: His firſt and chiefeſt, upon which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives himſelf to ſtand upon a Rock, but Reader, obſerve how ſandy it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, we dare be bold to affirm, that his whole building will fall, if this be the only Rock and ſupport of it.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119878:33"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sacraments</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum viſibile, <hi>a viſible Goſpel; The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments ſet forth Chriſt to the eye, as the Goſpel doth to the ear, therefore the ſame latitude in the Administration of both.</hi> This is the ſubſtance of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there be the ſame latitude of adminiſtring the Goſpel and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, then to whomſoever the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is preacht, the Sacraments are alſo to be adminiſtred. The Goſpel is preacht to all the world, therefore all the world to take the Sacrament. Sir, you know well enough that the Apoſtles preacht the Goſpel to whole Cities, yea Nations, but adminiſtred the Sacraments only to ſuch as came and profeſſed repentance and ſubjection to the Lord Jeſus. Upon this ſcore, as many as hear the Goſpel preached, profeſſing to be converted or not converted, may come and eat bread and wine with the Church at pleaſure. A monſtrous profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>But his reaſon is, <hi>Becauſe this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhews forth the death of Chriſt, and this is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Pauls judgment of Chriſts Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Sir, To whom did it ſhew forth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119878:33"/>the Lords death, and who were to uſe it for that end? Were they not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Saints of <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſuch that had <hi>given up themſelves to the Lord by the will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Briefly, let it be ſhewed, that Jeſus Chriſt did inſtitute Sacraments for any other then profeſſing beleevers, or make any promiſe to them for converſion, or whether they were ever adminiſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any but ſuch as owned and ſubmitted to the Church: But he will not ſure ſay, the Goſpel is to be preacht to no other, therefore there is not the ſame latitude in the adminiſtration of both.</p>
            <p>But he further urgeth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. for this, <hi>O ye Galathians, before whom Chriſt hath been ſet out, as crucified among you. This expreſſion,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>may well be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True, it may be, but it is clear it was not the Apoſtles meaning there, but the doctrine of Chriſt crucified, from the power of which they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting.</p>
            <p>But grant it were, What doth he gain by it? It only will prove, that the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> (as a Church) received the Lords Supper, and that Chriſt was ſet out to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119878:34"/>the eye of a beleever; What's this to prove the ſame latitude of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel and adminiſtring Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>He is willing to prove it further by a Metaphor; <hi>A man covenants with a Landlord about a purchaſe, the price being paid, the bargain eſtabliſht, he comes and requires his Seal for confirmation; So Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt makes a purchaſe for us, gives us the writing and ſeal in the Goſpel and Sacrament.</hi> This is the ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Very true, but muſt not the <hi>party</hi> for whom this purchaſe is made come firſt and accept of the bargain upon its own terms, and ſo have it ſealed to his uſe? ſo muſt not every ſoul firſt profeſs to accept Jeſus Chriſt on his own terms, and ſo the Church in the name of Chriſt to give him the ſeal, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a Prince proclaims a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don upon condition of laying down their arms, and ſo gives forth a pardon and ſeal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>So Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But muſt not then the rebel firſt lay down his arms, and profeſs ſubjection <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo muſt not every ſoul profeſs laying down their ſins, and to ſubject to Chriſt?</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119878:34"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will it not be plain, as We offer the conditions to any, ſo may we the ſeal,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="1">1. True, we offer pardon of ſinne, the condition, as he cals it, but we are not to apply the ſeal, unleſs there be a profeſſed acceptance of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If a ſoul do firſt <hi>accept</hi> of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, or do not break them by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in ſinne, then he is to have the ſeal: But what doth all this make for his purpoſe? If he intend by this that all that ſubmit to the Goſpel-terms and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, which are <hi>repentance, faith</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> that they ought to have the Goſpel-ſeal, the Sacrament, who will contend with him? This doth not ſure prove the ſame latitude in preaching the Goſpel and adminiſtring Sacraments. The Goſpel may be preacht to thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands who may not <hi>accept</hi> of the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it.</p>
            <p>We will here urge the Argument of that learned Divine <hi>Parcus</hi> on <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Catech. de diſ.</note> againſt this judgement; ſaith he, The ſigns are to be adminiſtred to none but to whom the promiſe belongs, but this belongs not to wicked impenitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; Therefore; His reaſon he gives,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119878:35"/>is that which ſpeaks juſt contrary to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> aſſertion; If the Church ſhould adminiſter the ſigns of grace to ſuch, <hi>Verbo viſibili abſolveret, quos verbo audibili damnaret.</hi> The Church would abſolve in the viſible Word, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whom He doth condemn in the audible Word, the Goſpel, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares no unbeliever, or wicked perſon, as ſuch, to have inheritance in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; If no inheritance, then not the ſeals of that inheritance: But we have ſtood too long upon this, which we the rather do to undeceive the weak.</p>
            <p>But yet, there is ſo much ſtreſs laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this his Argument, that it is backt with four conſiderations.</p>
            <p>His firſt, <hi>The Goſpel is to be preacht to every creature, and a baptizing them, therefore this Sacrament alſo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What is this but a repeating the ſame thing? But was every ſoul baptized that had the Goſpel preacht to it? Doth it not run, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15. <hi>He that beleeveth and is baptized,</hi> &amp;c,</p>
            <p>Why will men offer to ſtagger weak ſouls with ſuch inconſequent reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:119878:35"/>
            <p n="2">2. His ſecond conſideration, <hi>That the Goſpel offers Chriſt freely to all,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>without qualifications (ſo there be a preſent giving up himſelf ſincerely to him) And yet none but ſuch as ſhall be qualified after their mindes muſt come to the Sacrament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But would he have no qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations upon a ſoul that comes to the Sacrament, no repentance, no faith? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth not his <hi>ſincere giving up himſelf unto the Lord as his Lord and Saviour</hi> imply theſe? But what if this ſoul ſhould before the Miniſter and Church before he comes to this Ordinance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that in ſincerity (ſo farre as he knows his own heart) he doth give up himſelf to the Lord and his people? Would this take off from the free tender of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Further, ſaith he, <hi>Is Chriſt offered as a free gift in the Word, and muſt we not come Without our price and money to this Ordinance?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Authors ingenuity were deſirable here; Do the Preachers when they call for Repentance and faith in ſuch as come to this Ordinance, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table converſation, do they make this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119878:36"/>buying of Chriſt? Beſides, The Word is to begin and work faith; this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſuppoſeth faith; for it is ſuppoſed the bargain's made before the convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is ſealed; that a ſoul receives Chriſt, before Chriſt ſeals his love to him.</p>
            <p>His third conſideration, <hi>That the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel way is the beſt way to bring ſouls to Chriſt; Let,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a mans heart be fully convinced of the free grace of God in Christ, his heart can ſtand it no longer out againſt his converſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is true, but what to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in his Argument? Is every mans heart ſo convinced that hears the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel? He muſt firſt profeſs to have his heart convinced of the free grace of Chriſt, before he can rationally deſire the ſeal, or it can rationally be given unto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aye but,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when the Word is preacht, Covenant opened, Seal applied, the Meſſage of reconciliation comes in its full vertue to convince,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, keep to your rule, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel way is the beſt way, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Was this ever the Goſpel way, or is it any where preſcribed in it? Was not conviction
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119878:36"/>alwayes profeſt <hi>before</hi> either Sacrament was adminiſtred? We are well aſſured he cannot ſhew any precept or exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the contrary in the Goſpel. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this huddling of things will not paſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His fourth conſideration, ſure a haſty one, is this, <hi>The Goſpel is a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Goſpel, an embaſſie of peace, now how ſhall this peace be kept if we go to make ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at this Ordinance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The truth is, a ſufficiently worldly and carnal Argument; but, Reader obſerve, may not the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be urged againſt the preaching of the Goſpel too? Doth not this breed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, is not this reaſoning directly againſt what Chriſt himſelf delivers ſhall be the effect of the preaching of the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.33, 34. <hi>I came not to ſend peace but a ſword; I am come to ſet a man at variance againſt his father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And a mans foes ſhall be thoſe of his own houſe,</hi> &amp;c. And elſwhere, <hi>I will gather you one of a family, and two of a City,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p>Now is not the Goſpel a Goſpel of peace (that is, to the ſoul which receives
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119878:37"/>it, in which ſenſe it is an embaſſie of peace) becauſe it will make ſuch work in the world, by the oppoſition of men againſt it? May it not as well be ſaid, O the Goſpel will make diſturbance? How ſhall the peace be kept? Whereas it is on purpoſe to ſeparate the kingdom of Chriſt from the world? The truth is, this argument is of ſo little weight, that therefore ſuch a ſeparation as keeps off ignorant and profane perſons from the Supper, ought to be, becauſe it will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the conſciences of ſuch, and may (by grace) awaken them to a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their own condition, and not longer be flattered in the cuſtomary car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal way they have been lulled aſleep in: He next ſtates the caſe of a poor wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſinner, as if it were meant any ſuch ſhould be kept off by godly men who plead for the purity of this Ordinance; We plead againſt ſuch as are <hi>whole</hi> in their own opinions, ignorant, profane, revilers, and not wounded ſinners, if they declare themſelves poor ſinners and wounded, no doubt but they will be received.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not adde any thing to the other part of this conſideration, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119878:37"/>but a repeating of what is before ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Reaſon is <hi>drawn from the nature of a viſible Church, which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a number of ſuch as make profeſſion of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo are Saints by calling, whatſoever they are in truth, the eſſential marks whereof (whereby it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts as viſible) is the preaching the Word, and adminiſtring Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not to diſpute this, How far the preaching of the Word and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Sacraments are eſſential marks: The Word may be preacht to thoſe that are no Church, and the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments adminiſtred to a falſe Church; Ordinances are rather food and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Church, then the marks of it.</p>
            <p>There may be Churches in a large ſenſe, that may have no right Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtitution, and yet have theſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as begun meerly by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Magiſtrate to ſubject to ſuch forms he preſcribes, and not by the preaching of the Goſpel, and a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſubmiſſion of a people to it; and ſuch are not properly <hi>Saints by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> It is poſſible there may be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119878:38"/>ſuch Congregations in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Will you ſtile affected-ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſcoffers at inſtruction and the power of godlineſs, obſtinate hereticks, Saints by calling, though they make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Jeſus Chriſt? Surely this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Therefore it may be added that a Church is <hi>coetus fidelium,</hi> a ſociety of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers that profeſs Chriſt and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and practiſe anſwerably, and are anſwerably united by mutual agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who ſubmit freely to Chriſts Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</p>
            <p>But he goeth on, <hi>Now unleſs men will be ſo bold, as to diveſt our mixt Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of the name of the viſible Church, they cannot take away one eſſential note, in the free uſe of this Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But, Sir, there is much differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between the reforming of a Church, that there may be a due and juſtifiable uſe of this Ordinance, and a taking of it away, which we know none but fanatick perſons who deny the uſe of this Ordinance to do.</p>
            <p>But he will prove, <hi>That our mixt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations ought to have the uſe of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, both from Chriſts doctrine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119878:38"/>
            <p>His Doctrine, <hi>In the Parables of the little and great fiſhes in one net, good and bad called to one feast, the chaff and wheat in one barn, tares and wheat in one field,</hi> Mat. 13. <hi>which muſt grow together till the day of Judgement, and ſo no ſeparation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Briefly, Thoſe tares we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, with moſt reformed Expoſitours, to be cloſe hypocrites, and nor of open profane perſons and revilers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Miniſtry, and of the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, elſe to what purpoſe doth he elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſpeak of Excommunication, which is to caſt ſuch as pretend to be Chriſts friends, but walk as his enemies, out of the Church? And if under pretence of this, all ungodly blaſphemous wretches, groſs ignorants, muſt be admitted: What difference between the Church and the Kingdom of the devil?</p>
            <p>We allow there is no ſeparation from cloſe hypocrites, <hi>De occultis non judicat Eccleſia.</hi> But as to open, diſcovered, ſcandalous perſons, the Church is to caſt them out; or if they are the greater part, to withdraw from them, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
            <p>If it be reply'd, That the ſervants knew them to be tares, therefore not
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119878:39"/>cloſe hypocrites: We anſwer, That godly Miniſters may diſcern hypocrites with a knowledge of probability, and ſo theſe ſervants might diſcover the tares; ſpecially if by <hi>Zizania</hi> theſe tares are meant burnt ears of corn, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Leigh,</hi> M, <hi>Trap</hi> and <hi>Weems,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is alſo ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.25. <hi>While men ſlept the enemy ſowed tares;</hi> Where Chriſt imputes it to the remiſneſs and ſleepineſs of the ſervants, the Miniſters, that tares came into and were ſuffered in the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By thoſe tares, Chriſt doth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, ſuch who are not openly and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſcandalous, but ſuch tares who are much like the wheat (as <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith thoſe kinde of tares were) elſe he would contradict himſelf, in commanding ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous perſons to be caſt out of the Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. and yet here to command them to let them alone.</p>
            <p>To conclude his Argument he breaks out in Rhetorick, <hi>Who Lord dare antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate thy throne to ſeparate?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>None, we hope, <hi>viz.</hi> to undertake to ſeparate all cloſe hypocrites out of the Church, as hath been ſaid; but there are ſome who may and ought to be ſo
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119878:39"/>bold (whereof we believe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys,</hi> and his Church to be a part) to exerciſe that power Chriſt hath left them to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Churches from <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution;</hi> elſe all Chriſts threatnings to the Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> for continuing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, blaſphemy, lukewarmneſs among them, commending them that could not bear the evil had been vain; What elſe indeed is the Church of Chriſt, but ſuch a ſeparation of believers from the pollution and wickedneſs of the world?</p>
            <p>Next he would prove it from Chriſts example, <hi>Who converſed with Publicans and ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This will ſerve, as it hath ever done, the turns of the profane people to urge againſt the ſtrict and reſerved carriage of the godly, in not frequently mixing in their companies, as they abuſe this Scripture; but it is ſad to have it ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by a Miniſter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe Chriſt converſed with Publicans and ſinners to convert them, therefore did he admit them, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Family, and give them the ſeals of his love, which muſt be the import of the Argument, if it pretend to prove
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119878:40"/>any thing; If you had Infidels dwelling near you, becauſe you did ſometime converſe with them, Would it be a good Argument for any to urge againſt you, that you therefore gave them the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Were Publicans and ſinners ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for his Diſciples, or to his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, till called and became followers of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>But now comes in the invincible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>viz. That Chriſt ate the Paſſeover and his own Supper With Judas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſhall for brevities ſake avoid this conteſt, Whether Chriſt did give the Supper to <hi>Judas.</hi> The Author paſſeth by the many preſſing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are given to the contrary by many learned men, ſpecially M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Gille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Only this, It is not likely that the Lord Jeſus ſhould ſay to one who was about to betray him, <hi>Take, eat my body, which was given for thee?</hi> for if <hi>Judas</hi> received it, Chriſt ſpake to him with the reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If it be replyed, That Chriſt dealt as an ordinary Miniſter in this admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, then it will help to fortifie the anſwer we chiefly ſtick to (ſuppoſing we
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119878:40"/>grant him that <hi>Judas</hi> did receive, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) which is, That Chriſt dealt as an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſter, and ſo <hi>Judas</hi> was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a cloſe hypocrite. Beſides, <hi>Judas</hi> had not committed the finne, as yet, and ordinary Miniſters do not uſe to keep any from the Sacrament for ſins they fear they may hereafter commit, but have not yet committed them.</p>
            <p>Now all that will not admit of his aëry free Admiſſion, are wilfully blinde, as he concludes, cenſoriouſly enough, againſt the judgement of moſt famous holy Divines, both ancient, reformed and modern, as ever the world was bleſt with ſince the Apoſtles times. This may gain opinion with his Pariſhioners, but not with the godly wiſe.</p>
            <p>His third reaſon is, <hi>From the nature of Christian Communion and Church-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, which ought,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to be in charity and humility, without judging,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to judge others better then themſelves, ſpecially in the Miniſter, from</hi> 2 Tim. 2.24, 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. As to Church-fellowſhip, <hi>The fellowſhip of Saints with the Father, and with Jeſus Chriſt, and one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> by mutual union and free agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119878:41"/>in the Lord. There's ſure but little footſteps of it in the moſt parochial frames.</p>
            <p>How were they united into ſuch a holy fellowſhip? Is a coming together of groſly ignorant, ſwearers, profaners of the Sabbath, abetting and pleading for all ungodlineſs, haters of ſuch as are godly, like a fellowſhip of Saints, as the Primitive Churches were? We may boldly return this Argument upon M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Church-fellowſhip, is a holy fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Saints walking in the light, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3, 7. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.6. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8, 9, 10, 11. 'Tis not a fellowſhip of Saints and devils (appearing even to be ſo) of light and darkneſs; therefore all manner of wretched perſons, wallowing in all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and profaneneſs; ought not to be received into it.</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, <hi>It ought to be in humility and charity,</hi> yea men profeſſing Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ought ſo to walk together, and all for bearance as to one anothers infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be uſed. But what kinde of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is this to admit ungodly perſons, as the members of Jeſus Chriſt, walking indeed as the members of Satan: So the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119878:41"/>truth is, profane people cry out, Oh you-muſt have charity! The reforming Miniſters have no charity, and the like; when too many have equivalently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced every part and article of their Covenant made to God in baptiſm, not minding to renew it; yet they blame us as uncharitable, becauſe we will not flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them in their abominations with the precious ſeal of Chriſts love, when they walk as his enemies, and have their mouths open againſt all goodneſs; That this is the temper of moſt, witneſs the preaching of all godly Miniſters.</p>
            <p>Now what a kinde of charity were this? Oh, mercileſs flattering pity!</p>
            <p>Again, we beſeech you to remember, that Church-fellowſhip muſt be as well in holineſs as in charity, here is no pleading for purity, but all for peace and charity.</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, <hi>We ought to judge others better then our ſelves;</hi> but Sir, this ſure was ever preſt upon ſuch as profeſſed Saintſhip in the Churches of Chriſt, not of ſuch, who though they will be good Chriſtians in their own and others eſteem, do yet hate the name of Saint, and revile it; ſuch an humble Chriſtian
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119878:42"/>is not in the greateſt humility, to eſteem better then himſelf, as the grace of Chriſt hath diſtinguiſhed him.</p>
            <p>But he puts an <hi>eſpecially</hi> to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for this excellent humility and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he is to be patient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Did ever any man underſtand that Scripture of adminiſtring Sacraments, but himſelf?</p>
            <p>Beſides, though this is to be a Miniſters carriage, yet one duty doth not claſh with another, he ought to do his duty alſo, to keep Chriſts Ordinances pure, and to try the people he is ſent to,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh,</hi> but ſaith he, <hi>If we muſt go cenſuring one anothers worthineſs, 'tis the ready way to heart-burnings,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We have before anſwered, that we take leave to call this but a very carnal Argument, Chriſt came not to give ſuch a kinde of peace between Saints and the wicked.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this ſtrikes at all Diſcipline, which muſt not hence be exerciſed for fear of heart-burnings. It may indeed make the Miniſters many enemies; The Lord grant this be not too great a ſnare upon many; free Admiſſion makes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119878:42"/>much for the <hi>eaſe, peace</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> of a Miniſter in the world: but it maketh him an unfaithfull ſteward of the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God.</p>
            <p>Now, to crown all, he is pleaſed to adde, <hi>That it is but a rigid Phariſaiſm to deny free Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, You have abundantly gratified prophane people (into whoſe hand your Book comes) and helps on the old accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of godly Miniſters and people, <hi>viz.</hi> That all this ſtrictneſs they pretend to, is but Phariſaiſm and hypocriſie; your ſinne and doom is 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2.</p>
            <p>We do not plead for <hi>rigidneſs</hi> truly ſo called; Godly Miniſters invite the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to profeſs repentance, and faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo to be received into Communion: but for the withholding of the holy things of Chriſt from ſtubborn perſons who <hi>ſcorn</hi> ſuch profeſſion, is no more then Chriſt commanded M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> and us to practiſe.</p>
            <p>The compariſon of the <hi>Phariſee</hi> and <hi>Publican</hi> is the old charge of the luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm carnal party againſt <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of godlineſs: Oh, ſay they, theſe will be holy, they are ſo ſtrict, juſt like the Phariſees; Why? becauſe they will not
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119878:43"/>partake with them in the unfruitfull works of darkneſs, and now would not be guilty of their Sacrament-ſins, which they are, if they do not their duty to keep them off.</p>
            <p>Next, he breaks out with a pathetical expoſtulation and prayer, <hi>Rebuke the humour of theſe times, Oh my Saviour!</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Reformation is but a humour, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys;</hi> Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus rebuke the profaneneſs of theſe times, and let not thy holy things be thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted! Rebuke them that call evil good, and good evil.</p>
            <p>Another he follows with, <hi>That ſince Chriſt offered himſelf to ſinners, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver caſt out any that came, Shall any take ſtomack he is offered in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is the former confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things that ought to be diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; If a ſoul profeſs to <hi>come</hi> to Chriſt, that is, to ſubject to him, and walk with his people, who will deny him the Seal? Doth it therefore follow that the Lords Supper is to be given to thoſe who do not <hi>come</hi> to him, and being call'd upon <hi>will not</hi> profeſs to do ſo?</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:119878:43"/>
            <p>But let us enquire, Doth the Author of <hi>free Admiſſion</hi> conceive, that Jeſus Chriſt would have admitted Publicans and ſinners to his Supper without any more ado? Were they not firſt to be received as Diſciples? Here's his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Chriſt ſometimes converſt with Publicans and ſinners, therefore all may come to the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>His next Scripture is <hi>John</hi> 8. about the adultreſſe woman, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>He that is without ſinne, caſt a ſtone at her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was to check the proud Phariſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm of others, who ſcorn'd her out of vain-glory, when they themſelves were guilty of as great ſins; Muſt therefore adultereſſes without profeſſed humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Church be received to the Lords Supper? Though a beleever finds the ſame corruption in himſelf, and is abaſed in it, yet he ſees himſelf diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht through grace from an unhum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled adultreſſe, from ſuch that live in open ſcandalous ſins, which he pleads for to come to this holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p>His fourth reaſon ſpeaks high words, <hi>Which doth ariſe from the vanity, formality,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119878:44"/>impoſſibility of ſelecting people to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prove either of theſe diſtinctly, nothing is offered, onely ſomething in the general; 1. <hi>Look but to the heart of theſe ſeparations, and they come to nothing.</hi> This is as ſlightly as uncharitably ſpoken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If he means by ſeparations, the uniting of ſuch as profeſs repentance and faith before the Lord and his people into a cloſer fellowſhip, that all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances may be rightly adminiſtred: We anſwer, Theſe ſeparations, bleſſed be the name of the Lord, came to ſomething, and the good hand of the Lord is with them, and hath gloriouſly appeared for them. But to ſpeak plainly, we wonder what the mixt Parochial Congregations for the moſt part came to, if we look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the leaſt of them, where no Church-Reformation is practiſed, even the very leaſt of them is carnal, formal, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted worſhip, no fellowſhip toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor mutual edification, but ſetled upon the dead lees of formality, and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered to their own deſtruction in ſuch a condition by a continued enjoyment of all Ordinances, without any diſcovery
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119878:44"/>(but by meer coming to the Ordinances) that they ſo much as pretend to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides, godly men doe not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, but invite all upon profeſſion of owning the Lords Covenant, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He puts the caſe, <hi>You will have a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd company, Whom would you admit, if not all that make profeſſion, as we do mixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then thoſe only who have an intereſt in Chriſt and true believers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We know not well what he means by <hi>making profeſſion as they do;</hi> What profeſſion he means; If he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it of all people in the Nation making profeſſion, ſuch as it is, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite profeſſion, becauſe they come to the Ordinances; we do not account this a ſufficient profeſſion (and ſo the Brethren of both wayes call for explicite profeſſion, and a converſation not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that profeſſion) for Atheiſts and all profane perſons come to Church, as he ſtileth it, who revile the preaching of the Goſpel, if it be powerfull, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and wallow in all manner of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, making no more of the name of God and Lord in their mouths, then
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119878:45"/>of the name of a beaſt, as is the moſt common practice of much the greater part; and if they be called upon to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt, repentance, faith, before the Miniſter or others, they hate and ſcorn it.</p>
            <p>Now if he means by ſuch a bare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal profeſſion, without any regard to knowledge or converſation, we deny it to be enough, if this be all they mixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if in gathering a Church, you receive not all that make profeſſion mixtly, as they do (that is, as we conceive ſuch as we have deſcribed) then only ſuch as are true believers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here lies a fallacy; Such as would gather companies, as he cals it, or unite people into a cloſer communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Churches may be purer, have a middle way between his mixt profeſſion and true believing, that is, an explicite profeſſion of repentance and faith, and confeſſing of Chriſt, and not denying this in the tenour of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations: And of theſe indeed we do not pretend to be able to know them who are <hi>true</hi> believers, and who are not. What Reverend M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith in this
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119878:45"/>caſe, is moſt true, in his learned Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Baptiſm; <hi>The judgement may be falſe, but the rule of judging infallible,</hi> which is by explicite profeſſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
            <p>In that <hi>Pag.</hi> 23. he ſeems to impoſe upon godly Miniſters, as if they went about to have Churches without hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites. No, ſure they would have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward viſible purity, as much as may be, they would have their Churches like the Communion of Saints, and not a den of thieves. They know <hi>that a little lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven leaveneth the whole lump,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. how much more danger of the Lords diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, when even the whole lump is near leaven'd with ignorance, profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, enmity to Godlineſs; They would not keep up ſuch frames of Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> lukewarm formality, which the Lord profeſſeth to abhorre, and ſpue out of his mouth from being Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>He there further ſpeaks of a <hi>formall purity.</hi> We contend, as much as may be for a <hi>reall</hi> purity, and power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; but ſuch as live in open and known profaneneſs have not ſo much as a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal purity.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119878:46"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And as for ſeparation upon ſeparation, as in the peeling of his Onyon, which may cauſe men to weep.</hi> We would not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with his jeſts in holy things; But we hope and pray that the Lord will give M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humfreys</hi> a heart to weep in private, and that bitterly for the grieving moſt of the godly of the Nation, and laying a ſtumbling block in the wayes of the Lords people, and making the hearts of the wicked to rejoyce; as we are ſure this piece of his hath abundantly done.</p>
            <p>His fourth reaſon, <hi>Is gathered from, the uniformity of the ſervice of God; That all other worſhip lies in common, then it is an entrenchment upon the common liberty, to put an encloſure upon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That uniformity of Gods worſhip in this matter, coſt the holy Preachers of this Nation dear under the Biſhops. Oh! that it ſhould be again pleaded for!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>all worſhip ought to lie in common.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet Chriſt cals his Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12. <hi>A garden encloſed; And a vineyard of red wine,</hi> Iſa. 27.2. and many the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119878:46"/>(to ſay no more) as any fell from his pen; The Diſcipline of the Church hath heen uſually ſtiled the hedg and fence of the Church, to preſerve it from ruine and pollution, and now muſt all be in common?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>'Tis an entrenchment</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>upon the Common Liberty;</hi> 'Tis indeed a reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>curſed</hi> liberty, that ever we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve was pleaded for by a man pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fear the Lord; All in common to Atheiſts, Drunkards, Swearers, Revilers, ignorant perſons, now, <hi>all in common,</hi> and yet he would make us beleeve he is a friend to Diſcipline: But now we have a fetch, <hi>Are not</hi> ſaith he <hi>all the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God univerſall, why not Do this alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sir, We beſeech you to whom was <hi>Do this,</hi> in the adminiſtration of the Supper ſpoken to? Was it to <hi>all</hi> that ever heard Chriſt preach, or only to his 12 Apoſtles?</p>
            <p>Further, He urgeth, <hi>If an unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man can do nothing but ſin in all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, why muſt he be kept from this more then other, why a more fear of his ſin here?</hi> This the ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the other Ordinances
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119878:47"/>of the Word and prayer are for his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, this ſuppoſeth men converted in a judgement of charity, and ſo right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>received</hi> and continued in the Church according to Chriſts order. A wicked man is <hi>abſolutely</hi> forbidden to receive the Lords Supper, and none commanded to come but he who hath proved himſelf fit by examination, but there lieth an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>command</hi> upon <hi>all</hi> men to <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>pray;</hi> As to his Grammar Allegory to the Independents of <hi>Heteroclites</hi> and <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxis; That they allow a Syntaxis in the whole worſhip of God, but make Hetoroclites at the Sacrament,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis likely it is becauſe they would keep a <hi>true Syntaxis</hi> and <hi>godly order</hi> in their Churches, and not admit of <hi>Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roclites, viz.</hi> prophane wretches and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſers of holineſſe into it; what is <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> but to keep off ſuch <hi>Heteroclites</hi> from the fellowſhip of the Church, and ſpecially in this Ordinance? As to the practice of ſuch <hi>Presbyterians</hi> as baptize the Children of all, but not admitting all to the Supper, we ſhall not ſay much of it: Learned men conceive from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.23. <hi>We are all baptized into one Body whether Jews or Gentiles,</hi> that <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119878:47"/>into the univerſall Church; It doth not therefore follow that ſuch a one hath priviledge in a <hi>particular</hi> Church of all Ordinances, unleſſe his profeſſion made in baptiſm be perſonally received, and ſo he <hi>joyn</hi> himſelf to a particular Church; but have the people of <hi>England</hi> in Pariſh Churches ever done ſo? ſpecially ſuch as are obſtinately ignorant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane: But for ſuch perſons who cannot be judged either of theſe, as to the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of their Infants, we leave godly men to their own practice, as they ſhall ſee it moſt conducing to reall Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>His ſixth Reaſon is drawn [<hi>from his own innocency in thus doing, in admitting all to the Supper.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We beleeve it will not be found his <hi>innocency</hi> (without deep repentance) in the day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Saith he [<hi>I do but my duty</hi>] That's but the Queſtion beg'd; We deny it to be ſo upon the terms he goeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He hath no power to turn away any;</hi> We will not diſpute this with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if he <hi>had power,</hi> by his own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples he <hi>ought not</hi> ſo to do, for he argues all are to come, good and bad; Or if
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119878:48"/>he would exerciſe <hi>Diſcipline</hi> 'tis his own fault, he draws not on thoſe who will <hi>ſubmit</hi> to it with him, and ſo pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith, <hi>He hopes the beſt of all,</hi> But Sir, Is the meer coming of a perſon ground enough for hope without any diſcovery or triall of him? and when he lives in known ſins and never profeſſeth acceptance to the Church! How can he call this ground enough for his hope? He will ſure preach the contrary to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that 'tis not ground enough to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and why ſhould they then be <hi>flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered</hi> in ſuch a hope by the Sacrament? which is indeed the great miſchief we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend comes by <hi>free admiſſion;</hi> Oh that there were ground enough of preſent hope upon the body of the people of this Nation? If M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Humphreys</hi> Congregation be not peerleſſe, ſure he may queſtion his ground of hope upon too many, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>God can turn the moſt at his Ordinances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But ſhew us where he hath <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed</hi> he will, or any <hi>example</hi> of it; 'tis not good arguing from <hi>Gods omnipotency</hi> to his <hi>ordinary</hi> way of dealing; if a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man were in Gods way to converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119878:48"/>at the Lords Supper he might expect a bleſſing, but he is out of Gods way, and therefore he hath no ground to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect converſion, or we to ſuppoſe it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>I endeavour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my utmoſt that all come prepared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> For a Miniſter to do <hi>his utmoſt</hi> in this caſe, yea, what <hi>de jure</hi> of right he ought to do is a great matter: we know not the Authours particular practice, but we conceive if he doth no more then what we can gather, he is far from doing his <hi>utmoſt duty,</hi> unleſſe he <hi>reprove, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, exhort,</hi> even <hi>one by one,</hi> we mean all that are admitted, as <hi>Paul</hi> did the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. we beleeve he is bound in this <hi>Corruption of times</hi> to call upon all to come and own the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the Lord their God, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Chriſt, and to give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord in a fellowſhip toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or elſe we humbly conceive he doth not the <hi>utmoſt</hi> of his duty.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>He confeſſeth the ſins of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But ought not every ſinner upon a due receiving into the fellowſhip of the Church to confeſſe himſelf a ſinner, and his loſt condition in himſelf before the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119878:49"/>Lord, and his people in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, He addes, <hi>He might further prove from the command and good of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and from the evil of omitting it, the Sacrament is a means and a pledge, a means to receive grace, and a pledge to aſſure.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis a means of receiving <hi>more</hi> grace, but not the <hi>firſt</hi> grace; <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Suppoſe a poor Soul wants grace, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall he come but to the means of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it?</hi> If he be a poor Soul in his own ſight and appehenſion, and ſo comes <hi>thirſting</hi> after grace, it ſuppoſeth grace begun. <hi>Bleſſed are they that thirſt,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo that proves nothing for his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Ordinances</hi> (ſaith he further) <hi>are the baths, there are many come to the Bath that are never the better for it, and yet they are means of health, and open toall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But Sir, Where do you finde this Allegory in the Scriptures, That all men may freely come to the Sacrament as to the <hi>Baths?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Such as come to the <hi>Bath</hi> come as <hi>ſick</hi> and <hi>weak,</hi> and <hi>pained,</hi> and ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Chriſt in his Ordinances ſhall finde healing; what's this to the <hi>whole who need not the Phyſician,</hi> as impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119878:49"/>ſinners and groſſe ignorant perſons are?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Baths are open and free to all:</hi> That is the abuſe of them, they are meant only for the <hi>ſick</hi> and <hi>pained,</hi> and ſo 'tis of Chriſts healing Ordinance of the Supper, 'tis the abuſe and that a great one, if any but ſuch as profeſſe to <hi>deſire healing</hi> of Chriſt be admitted to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That 'tis a means of conveying grace,</hi> he ſaith <hi>there is no great difficulty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If he means the firſt grace, 'tis ſuch a <hi>difficulty</hi> as he hath not unfolden in this Treatiſe; and to ſeek for the firſt grace from the uſe of the Supper is not of Gods ordaining, and is indeed a piece of will-worſhip; Faith cometh ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily only by the Word preacht.</p>
            <p>For the evil of omiſſion, <hi>p.</hi> 26. he ſaith, <hi>Thoſe that neglected the Paſſeover were out off,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> He may alſo remember that ſuch as had morall uncleanneſſe upon them were not to come, and if they did they were to be cut off from the Lords Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>He addes, <hi>In the Goſpel thoſe that came not to the Feaſt,</hi> Mat. 22. <hi>were deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:119878:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It hath been anſwer'd, that 'tis to be underſtood of the generall Call of the Goſpel, and not of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſpecially of the Jews, who were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for not receiving the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we are not to neglect a certain duty for fear of accidentall ſcandal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We deny it to be a <hi>certain duty</hi> to every ſoul but only to the <hi>really</hi> fit, as to themſelves, and <hi>viſibly</hi> fit as to the Church, to receive them. No abſolute command, no abſolute duty.</p>
            <p>His Admonition as to Preſumption in coming, the Lord alſo ſet home upon his own heart as to his preſumption in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting.</p>
            <p>Now we come to his ſecond Sermon, where he undertakes very <hi>curſorily</hi> to anſwer many Objections that Learned and Godly men have made againſt his judgement.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anſwer to the Second Sermon.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, As to his Preface, he ſaith, <hi>He is forced to ſerve in more words then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We beleeve it true, for it were better we dare ſay he had ſaid nothing; And
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119878:50"/>for his Prayer, <hi>That if his Book grieve any of the Lords little Ones</hi> (as we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it doth thouſands) <hi>that the Lord would blot out his Sermon and his ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>The firſt Objection he undertakes to anſwer, is, <hi>This doctrine will take the uſe of the keys and leave us no diſcipline.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he anſwers, 1. By way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, He grants a <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and that the want of it is to be bewailed, and yet hath <hi>a ſalvo</hi> a new one indeed, for this by anſwering that the Objection goes upon falſe ſurmiſes about excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſurmiſeth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Church-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline to lie in a ſuſpenſion from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For if that be the end of it, what is this but to gratifie a prophane perſon in keeping him from the Sacrament, who never inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or never cared to come thither?</hi> To this purpoſe he ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No, Will not <hi>prophane</hi> Perſons come? This is a large extenſion of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; there are we fear hundreds of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, may we not ſay thouſands? which cohſiſt of little elſe, and yet through cuſtome, if they have not the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119878:51"/>Communion once a year, and ſo go to play in their beſt cloathes afterwards, they will think themſelves greatly wronged.</p>
               <p>Briefly, That this is one end of Church-Diſcipline, to preſerve the honour of Chriſt and purity of his Ordinances, we do with all godly Writers upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, aſſent, and not only in reference to reforming the offender, as <hi>p.</hi> 32. he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf implyeth; It excludeth them from the fellowſhip of the Saints, whoſe <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip</hi> is chiefly in this Ordinance, and therefore cal'd the <hi>Communion,</hi> that ſo the fellowſhip of Saints may not be like the fellowſhip of the children of the devil.</p>
               <p>This inſinuates alſo <hi>No prophaning of this Ordinance more then the other,</hi> But Sir, was not there more care taken to prevent the profaning the Paſſeover un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, then the other ordinary worſhip, the hearing of the Law expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were not the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in a ſpeciall manner puniſhed for the prophaning of the Lords Supper; ſaith <hi>Pareus</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. on theſe words, <hi>This is not to eat the Lords Supper: Adeò tenera res eſt,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119878:51"/>Sacramentum; Non levitèr adulterant, ſed deſtruuut,</hi> &amp;c, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> It is not to eat the Lords Supper; 'Tis to <hi>deſtroy</hi> and make void the very nature of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, when ſo polluted by a prophane regardleſſe mixture.</p>
               <p>Pag. 33. Saith he <hi>[It ſuppoſeth a near eſſentiall relation between this Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and communion;]</hi> And ſo goeth on to refell it, which we need not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is no ſuch thing ſuppoſed in the Objection, Excommunication hath a <hi>relation of ſubſerviency</hi> to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, though not <hi>eſſentiall,</hi> but to the well-being of it, that holy things be not proſtituted nor given forth to ſuch as Chriſt never intended them, <hi>viz.</hi> his prophane enemies, or ſuch who refuſe his yoke, being called upon to profeſſe ſubjection to it.</p>
               <p>But he brings in one objecting: Is it not a heavy caſe that we have no diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline? <hi>True,</hi> ſaith he, yea, 'tis true, that when Jeſus Chriſt hath given power to his Churches to reform and exerciſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, they caſt the want of it upon the Magiſtrate, and doe nothing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:119878:52"/>
               <p>But what then, ſaith he, <hi>Shall we have no worſhip?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> No <hi>pure</hi> worſhip in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but ſuch as God and his holy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple abhorre.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Objection he undertakes to anſwer is, <hi>viz. That the moſt of men are wholly unfit, and not capable of this Ordinance, and not able to prepare and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine themſelves, therefore no free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a manifeſt weakneſſe in this arguing from mens diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to their duty: He conceits as to the Churches part, who can but look to an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward capacity, and inſtanceth in</hi> Judas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But Sir, as eaſily as you huſh up this Argument, 'Tis more to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and laid to heart, how <hi>unfit</hi> the moſt people are, having never had the preaching of the Goſpel with them in its power, <hi>in many places,</hi> nor were ever rightly ordered and conſtituted into a Goſpel-Church-ſtate, by a profeſſed ſubjection to the Goſpel, and giving up themſelves to the Lord, and ſo joyning together to walk in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, as we have ſhewed, which however men may skin over, we verily
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119878:52"/>beleeve the Lord will in his time manifeſt to be a holy truth.</p>
               <p>Now as to his anſwer, That <hi>'tis a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt weakneſſe to argue from mens unabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to their duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This hath been anſwered and cleared; 'Tis not every mans duty to come to the Sacrament, as we have diſtinguiſhed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſo and ſo prepared and qualified; Unability to prepare themſelves is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon to themſelves to refrain, and to the Church to keep them off: And whereas he ſaith, The Church is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to look to an outward capacity; Very true, if an outward capacity be rightly defined: But groſſe ignorance and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in open known ſins, and reviling of godlineſſe, is not an outward capacity; Which all along his Book upon his grounds, the meer name of a Chriſtian, though never ſo vile, is his <hi>outward ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next as to the Peoples part he anſwers 3. things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>There's no duty a naturall man can do rightly, nor hear, nor pray, therefore let him do nothing, let him have a Writ of eaſe for all,</hi> &amp;c. This is his firſt in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:119878:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> Firſt, Then it ſeems a naturall man ſo underſtood to be <hi>by himſelf and the Church,</hi> may come to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; Whereas M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humphreys</hi> well knows none but profeſſing Saints in a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of charity were ever admitted; if they be rightfully within the pale of the Church, they ought to be ſo eſteemed, nothing to the contrary appearing; but to make the ſame latitude of Prayer and the Word, with the Lords Supper, (the former for converting this of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only to ſuch as are ſuppoſed to be converted in the Judgement of the Church) is a monſtrous Solceciſme, Meer Heathens are allowed and invited to come to the one, never to the other; Now he is pleaſed to call this kinde of arguing againſt his judgement in this thing, <hi>Beating the air with a Feather.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir, Thoſe pillars of truth, that holy men have erected by the good hand of God againſt their looſe aiery tenet will ſtand, and be glorious in the eyes of the Lord and his people, when yours ſhall be for a hiſſing unto both. Is the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament enumerating abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſcandalous. crimes with advice had with the Aſſembly of Divines to
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119878:53"/>debarre perſons from the Lords Supper, nothing but <hi>beating the air with a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. His ſecond Anſwer, <hi>He would have every man do what he can,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Right, If a poor ſoul tender up himſelf to the Lord and his people, and complain of his weakneſs, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to do what by grace <hi>he is able,</hi> Who doubts of ſuch a mans fitneſs?</p>
               <p>His third Anſwer is, Stating of <hi>a poor humbled ſinner heavy laden with ſin, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold of the promiſe,</hi> &amp;c. As if any body ſcrupled ſuch a one, but inviteth them with all tenderneſs; what's this to a ſtubborn, ignorant, impenitent ſinner, that comes cuſtomarily, and returns to his ſin; and will not come near his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to be inſtructed in private, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileth him, if holy, as the moſt do?</p>
               <p>The third Objection, <hi>But is not the Ordinance taken in vain againſt the third Commandment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he Anſwers, <hi>He grants, on the Receivers part, but not on the Admitters, he is to do his duty, and leave the ſucceſſe to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is the Queſtion begg'd, we deny it the Admitters duty, if the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119878:54"/>perſons are ſcandalous, they are to keep the Sanctuary of the Lord from defiling; which duty being a <hi>minor</hi> Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, is ſuppoſed in the greater Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication put into the hands of Church-Officers, being one of the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven committed unto them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This duty is ſuppoſed, in keeping our ſelves pure from the blood of all men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In our duty of fidelity to the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In duty of fidelity to the peoples ſouls. His inſtances in Chriſts preaching of the Goſpel, inviting all, hath been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; He never invited all to the Lords Supper, nor did the Apoſtles till in Church-fellowſhip; if he account all the people of <hi>England</hi> fit in the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they are, to be continued in the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of the Church, and no need of Reformation and drawing in ſuch that will come under Diſcipline to a cloſer union and order in the Goſpel; then he not only pleads for this Free-Admiſſion, but ſtrikes indeed at the very root of all Reformation, which the truth is, this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious principle ſufficiently doth.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:119878:54"/>
               <p>The third Objection he would An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, <hi>Holy things to holy men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the Anſwer he here gives diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the minde of the Authour more then any:</p>
               <p>He diſtinguiſheth of holineſs, <hi>Outward, Inward:</hi> He ſaith, Outward holineſſe conſiſts in bare profeſſion, and name of Chriſtians, and ſo are Saints by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: That of inward holineſs we need not mention.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Repl.</hi> We reply to him, That bare profeſſion and name of Chriſtian is not enough to denominate Saints by Calling; even a whole Nation of people may take up the Name of Chriſtian, and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the Magiſtrates ſevere Law: As all the people of <hi>England</hi> did in the ſeveral former changes, and were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to hear the Service-Book, and to Receive once a year; theſe are not like Saints by calling; which is, when upon the preaching of the Goſpel to them, and the Call of it, they willingly profeſs to anſwer the Call of the Goſpel, and to give obedience to it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such as are ſtiled, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be Saints,</hi> or Saints by calling, are alſo ſaid to be <hi>ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119878:55"/>Paul</hi> in a judgement of charity, eſteemed the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to be ſuch; for he writes to the <hi>Church of God at Corinth.</hi> Now will M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> dare in his moſt extenſive charity to call ſuch who have taken up the Name of Chriſtian, and profeſſion upon a ſlender account, the Lord knoweth, ſuch as are men affected<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant, common ſwearers, unclean, revilers, prophaners of the Sabbath, to be ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus? Beſides, Sir, Is not knowledge and converſation required to make up viſible Saints, as well as bare profeſſion, and the Name of Chriſtian?<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Let every one that nameth the Name of Chriſt depart from iniquity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.18</note> Is not this to hold the truth in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs?<note place="margin">Tit. 1.16.</note> To profeſs to know God, but in works deny him? Oh how doth this kinde of arguing nuzzle poor creatures in their wofull condition, and heighten the wicked in their wickedneſs? ſay they, they are Saints by calling, they make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and have the Name of Chriſtians, and in hell they curſe Miniſters eternally for thus deluding them: Nay do not the moſt of people hate, yea many profeſs to hate the very name of <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and the very name of <hi>Saints,</hi> and moſt will
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119878:55"/>ſay They are not to be Saints on earth, but in heaven; Is this ſufficient outward holineſs?</p>
               <p>But ſaith he, <hi>A viſible Ordinance to a viſible Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That's true, If this viſible Church be rightly conſtituted and ordered; but if it be miſerably corrupted, and abound with all iniquity, as the moſt do; If the Lords ſervants ſhall labour to keep up ſuch corruptions, as this opinion doth, we may tremble whether the Lord will not even root out this viſible Church and profeſſion; as he threatens us often ſeverely in his Word.</p>
               <p>He further brings in an objection, <hi>viz. Do we not hereby make our ſelves one with the wicked with whom we joyn; and can we have communion with Chriſt and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He anſwereth by way of conceſſion, <hi>We do and muſt be one with all that joyn in the ſame profeſſion, as members of the ſame viſible Church, we are not one with them in their evil courſes, we diſclaim them wholly in the impiety of their converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What kinde of <hi>joyning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in profeſſion</hi> our Parochiall <hi>Churches</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:119878:56"/>have had, we will not now further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: All come to <hi>Church,</hi> and, as he ſaith, we may go to Church with all (wherein he bath gratified the ignorant with a corrupt notion) and few have any further notion of a Church, then the place they went in, nor what duties are required of Church-members one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and the Lord knoweth, and tis too apparent, there is no practiſe of them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But Sir, for the ſanctified ones of Chriſt Jeſus to joyn as one body in Church-fellowſhip with haters of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the power of it, Is it not to make themſelves one body with the wicked and unclean? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17, 18. though they make profeſſion, yet being wicked, Is not this to joyn as one body with the wicked? Bare profeſſion doth not take away their wickedneſs; now is not this a great abomination to make up ſuch a body to Jeſus Chriſt? Lord, theſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are good enough for thee, though corrupt and abominable: Beſides, are not ſuch members to be cut off, even chiefly for this reaſon, that Chriſts body ſhould not appear with the members of Satan?</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:119878:56"/>
               <p n="3">3. Is not there a duty in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. charged upon every Church-member to reprove his brother, ſo upon all the Churches by <hi>Paul,</hi> and is not every Church-member guilty of his brothers ſin, who doth not his duty in this thing?<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.14, &amp;c. 2 Theſ. 3.15.</note> ſpecially when they are to come together in this great Ordinance? But that indeed he pleads for, is for every one <hi>to look to himſelf</hi> (though a hint to the contrary in the cloſe) as he ſpeaks before; for regard to <hi>othere</hi> he much ſleights it; no matter for Chriſts honour in his worſhip or thy Brothers ſoul, every body ſave one if he can: A true note of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But, Sir, farther, are we not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the impieties of the wicked in this thing, in communicating with them? Is it not an impiety for men in ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to communicate? If then we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with them, we communicate in their impieties, ſpecially ſince a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt lieth upon every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant to labour the preventing his impiety, which doing not, they come to the Ordinance with ſinne upon their ſouls.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>I will go with the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edeſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119878:57"/>man alive to Church, but not to the Alehouſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> His <hi>going to Church</hi> we have ſpoken to: But, Sir, if you allow the wickededſt man alive to be in your Church truly ſo called, whereof you are a Paſtor, and joyn with him, and give him this Ordinance without particular admonition of him, not joyning with the better to keep him off; we tremble to conceive that the Lords hand will be upon you, and ſuch that make ſo ſlight of it.</p>
               <p>As to what he urgeth out of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> his remiſneſs (though otherwiſe a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious witneſs of the Lord) in point of Church-Cenſures, is not approved by the Godly Learned; we will therefore take notice of his Scriptures.</p>
               <p>The firſt Scripture is <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Every branch in me that beareth not fruit;</hi> he ſhould adde what follows, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he takes it away.</hi> Grant it be meant of Chriſts power at the laſt day, yet when ſuch a branch ſhall bring forth curſed fruit, or appear to bring forth no good fruit at all, and ſo appear not to be of Chriſts planting, he is to be cut off by the Church, as he allows by his Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication;
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119878:57"/>or elſe what will he make of that Ordinance?</p>
               <p n="2">2. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Goodwins</hi> Interpretation of this Scripture, in his <hi>Treatiſe of Growth,</hi> will ſalve it, if there were any difficulty in it, who reades it thus. <hi>Every branch that brings forth not fruit in men;</hi> and this, ſaith he, the Syriack Tranſlation makes for alſo; though they do ſome good, yet it is not fruit, becauſe not in Jeſus Chriſt; which may well allude to ſuch Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors who bring ſome kinde of fruit in profeſſion and moral converſation, but yet have no root in Chriſt; and for ſuch the Church proceeds not againſt, if they are duly taken into the Church, till their unſoundneſs appears by outward pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe; and though Chriſt doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly give forth command to the Church, to cut off viſibly unſound bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches here, tis enough he doth in other places.</p>
               <p>His ſecond Scripture is 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>There are ſome that deny the Lord that bought them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea ſuch in the words imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly going before as <hi>bring in damnable hereſies:</hi> Now though ſuch did thus apoſtatize, that were received into the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119878:58"/>Church, as bought by Chriſt (which is meant by their denying the Lord that bought them) muſt they be continued and admitted to the Lords Supper? then this is the argument, Such as bring in damnable hereſies, and deny Chriſt, may and ought to be admitted to the Lords Supper: It ſeems Turciſm and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity may well enough mix with M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> his good leave: We had thought at leaſt Hereticks were to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by 1 <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p>His next Scripture is <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 2.9. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>There are ſome that are ſanctified with the blood they trample upon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> From hence he would argue, Tramplers on the blood of Chriſt may come; How tender is M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> of his Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours blood?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they are ſaid to be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, though tramplers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That is, they were externally ſanctified or ſet apart in Baptiſm, but now by their Apoſtaſie and falling off from Chriſtianity, they did ſlight and ſcorn the blood of Chriſt, as a <hi>common thing,</hi> not worthy to be owned; Now what's this to his purpoſe? 'Tis ſaid,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119878:58"/>they had forſaken the Aſſemblies of the Church, <hi>v.</hi> 25. therefore they did not come to the Lords Supper; but were, indeed, ſuch as had ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>But yet tender M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfrey</hi> is pleaſed to ſtile theſe <hi>branches of Chriſt,</hi> though <hi>ungodly Profeſſors:</hi> It ſeems with him, <hi>ungodly Profeſſors, renouncers of the faith, tramplers upon the blood of Chriſt, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, damnable Heretiques,</hi> muſt be in a viſible eſteem, branches of Chriſt, and ſo admitted to all Church-Priviledges, even the choiceſt, the Seal of Chriſts Supper; for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> puts up an abſolute plea for them: What can a man more ſtrongly plead for the kingdom of the devil then this? We beleeve his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane party will be here aſhamed of him. Yet the confidence of the man is ſuch, that he cries Victory to himſelf and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, upon this moſt abſurd and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable arguing, and abuſing the holy Word of God: Obſerve Reader, he puts the ſtreſſe of his cauſe mainly upon it: If thou art ſo blinde, ſenſleſſe, and mad to beleeve him, he tels thee the <hi>matter is ended</hi> on his ſide.</p>
               <p>And further, <hi>That an outward hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119878:59"/>faith gives an outward Church right to the elements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deny it, if it appear to be but an <hi>hiſtorical</hi> faith, by an ungodly life.</p>
               <p>The fourth Objection he undertakes to anſwer is, <hi>The Seal is ſet to a blank, if all be admitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He Anſwers firſt by opening how the Sacramentis a Seal, <hi>Not of our faith, but of the Covenant on Gods part. Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Covenant and Seal remain firm, and all the unbelief in the world, cannot make it of no effect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Scripture ſaith, that Circumciſion to <hi>Abraham</hi> was the <hi>Seal of the righteouſneſſe of faith,</hi> Rom. 4.11.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it be the Seal of the Covenant on Gods part, as of one party being agreed, yet if a ſoul do not <hi>accept</hi> of, and <hi>agree to the terms</hi> of it, it is but as a <hi>blank</hi> to him, there being not a <hi>mutual aſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation</hi> and <hi>agreement</hi> on both parts, and ſo ſuch a ſoul hath no good by it: If by this he would encourage a poor trembling ſoul, who doubts of his faith, he may make uſe of it, 'tis not of ſuch we here diſpute of.</p>
               <p>But he puts the Objection forward,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119878:59"/>viz. <hi>Were it not abſurd for a man to ſet his Seal, where there hath been no agreement and tranſactions before? ſo do unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men, who come to the Sacrament with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that ſolemn giving up the ſoul to God, as he ought who enters into Covenant with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he Anſwers, <hi>That there are too many come abſurdly and wickedly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Though the receiver fail on his part in his ſolemn mutual engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (whereof he is to repent) yet as for the Miniſter and Church there is a true ſeal to a true Copy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now we reply to him, There is a true Seal to a true Copy, but not to be delivered to <hi>rebels,</hi> unleſſe they come <hi>profeſſing</hi> humbly to <hi>accept</hi> the terms of it: Here is the thing we ſtick at, we require, and ſo we verily beleeve doth the Lord, that the Receiver ought ſolemnly to profeſſe and give up himſelf to God, and enter into Covenant with him before he be admitted by them to the <hi>Seal</hi> of it, if the perſon do not this in ſincerity, let him look to that; but that he do it is the <hi>Churches</hi> part to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of him, without which we beleeve he cannot fully acquit the Church as he
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119878:60"/>undertake to do, <hi>p.</hi> 47. And without this, inſtead of (nothing) being <hi>out</hi> of order (as he ſpeaks) there is hardly any thing <hi>in</hi> order: Now if the receiver do this, the Miniſter and Church receive him in the judgement of Love, as a regenerate perſon; and ſo they do not ſin in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the Sacrament as a Seal on Gods part.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>The Sacrament ſeals ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally the truth of the Covenant freely to all, engaging them unto it, and the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and benefits of it to every ſingle perſon upon the terms, conditions, tenour of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> With this notion, which he ſaith hath layn as an Embryon a long time, he profeſſeth himſelf and another piercing Godly man to be converted with it: We ſhall not judge them in this their converſion, but take boldneſs from the deceit we have learned in our own hearts, That 'tis no hard matter to get diſtinctions to pacifie the conſcience in a troubleſom work, as the practiſe of Reformation is: We anſwer, the blood of Chriſt ſeals the Covenant of God, but when tis offered in the ſign of it, the Sacrament, it is to ſuch perſons, who
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119878:60"/>accept of the Covenant upon the terms and conditions of it (as himſelf ſpeaks) and of the blood of Chriſt thereby ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, and it ſeals to none but to them who have communion with the blood of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. therefore it doth not generally ſeal to all. The Sacrament is not ſaid to ſeal the Covenant to all; tis the Seal of the Covenant, but it ſeals it <hi>to</hi> none but to the Believer, who is to engage unto it, firſt, <hi>Sincerely,</hi> as to his own intereſt in it. Secondly, <hi>Profeſſedly</hi> and <hi>explicitly,</hi> as to the Churches ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: To ſeal any thing to a perſon, implies a reciprocall agreement. We humbly take leave to ſay, that as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth his greateſt ſatisfaction in this argument, his greateſt miſtake lies in it, in confounding of things that ought to be diſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>We ſay, the tender of the Covenant is firſt in the preaching of the Goſpel, upon which beleevers profeſſe to own and accept of, and enter into it, (not by a meer tacit coming) which having done before the Lord and the Church, then, as the Sacrament ſhall be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, the Seal is annexed to it, and a beleever receives the blood of Chriſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119878:61"/>Jeſus as a Seal of Gods promiſes <hi>in the remiſſion of his ſins,</hi> and ſo to every cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting perſon (profeſſing to do ſo) the Covenant is offered and ſealed to him, and to none other.</p>
               <p>Now in ſtead of this, we conceive through the whole Treatiſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> would have a Sacrament, which (being the Seal of the Covenant) is to be tendered to all, be they what they will, without any <hi>previous act</hi> of the Receivers, either <hi>confeſſion, profeſſion</hi> or <hi>covenanting</hi> with or before the Church, which was never the way of the Goſpel in admiſſion of Church-members, and ſo it holds the ſame in the uſe of the Supper, when though baptized they have never given any account of themſelves, or are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane in their lives.</p>
               <p>Further, he urgeth his ſubtile Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm to analyſe the whole argument,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Covenant,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>means thus, He that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved: adde, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,</hi> ergo <hi>I ſhall be ſaved. Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Sacrament ſeals to the</hi> major, <hi>not to the</hi> minor, <hi>to Gods own Word, not to ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, The <hi>major</hi> or firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is rather a conditionall promiſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119878:61"/>of the Covenant, then the Covenant it ſelf; and ſo the Sacrament ſeals condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally. But without theſe quirks, If the Sacrament ſeal to every Beleever, then if I adde, But I am a Beleever, then it ſeals to me: and though the Scripture do not ſpeak of any particular man, who is a Beleever, yet in ſuch a Syllogiſm it it ſpeaks as fully, and even as ſatisfying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a poor ſoul as if it did: Sir, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament ſeals the truth of mercy and grace and life to poor ſouls that come rightly to it, and not to abſtracted pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and notions, with which you puzzle weak people.</p>
               <p>Again, ſtick to the propoſition as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally applyed, the Sacrament ſeals to this, <hi>He that beleeveth ſhall be ſaved,</hi> and the Sacrament confirms it to him, then let none but ſuch as ſhall be charitably judged <hi>Beleevers</hi> profeſſing faith and obedience be admitted to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. The fifth Objection he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes to Anſwer,<note place="margin">Pag. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. The Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to all, therefore the ſeals nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he Anſwers, by diſtinguiſhing of the Covenant, <hi>ſometimes taken for the abſolute promiſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſometimes for the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119878:62"/>tenour of the Goſpel in Gods revealed will, and ſo it runs on theſe terms, Whoſoever beleeves ſhall be ſaved, and whether this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all, tis no queſtion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Tis true, ſalvation belongs to all in the tender of it, as himſelf ſaith in the next page; The conditional Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is tendred in the word, and ſealed to in the Sacrament: Now as the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is tendred in the Word, if ſouls profeſſe to accept of the tender of it, and to Covenant with him, then 'tis ſeald in the Sacrament. The Sacrament is a Seal between God and the Beleever, and ſuppoſeth beleeving, intended to Seal mercy to profeſſing covenanting Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and upon that ſcore the Church doth adminiſter it, receiving them as ſuch.</p>
               <p>Next, he declareth his own practiſe, That he ſhews his hearers the conditions of the Covenant, ſuch that accept of them, there the Seal of God is ready, let them put to their hands and ſeals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This the import.</p>
               <p>But Sir, Is it not more proper, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſatisfying, that ſuch perſons upon the tender of the Covenant, ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and profeſſe to own and enter into
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119878:62"/>the Covenant of God? Muſt all be done in a huddle the ſame hour, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be as mutes in this great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Would it not be for the honour of Jeſus Chriſt, that people with their own mouths confeſſe him, according to the meaſure God hath given them, more for the ſatisfaction of the Miniſter and Church, yea, and for the comfort of the Profeſſour, then thus hand over head to deal in this weighty matter? Special<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſince this was never had from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> as we have before open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who are ſo ſetled in a corrupt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, cuſtomary way in the uſe of this Ordinance, for the moſt part, That talk you of Covenant and Seal, and what you will, They muſt have the Communion, though to the great prejudice of their ſouls; And 'tis from theſe ſad corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the iniquity of former and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent times; As the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in their <hi>Plea for Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> That ſuch a Profeſſion and triall is firſt to be had of every perſon; ſeeing the abuſe of this Ordinance was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and horribly prophane.</p>
               <p>In the cloſe (ſaith he) <hi>This Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth more properly belong to him
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119878:63"/>who is not yet in Covenant with God, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing now he reſolves to enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a ſtrange doctrine, and we verily beleeve never ſtarted before, Here is ſtill the ſame confuſion; But Sir, In this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance doth not the Church (for here we deal with it upon this account, which is the Churches and Miniſters duty in this Ordinance) ſuppoſe every receiver in Covenant before, firſt as tendred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it in Baptiſm, and ſecondly, as requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a perſonall owning and profeſſing of the Covenant and the conditions of it (which was ever the practice of the Primitive Churches, as hath been urged) and ſo adminiſter the Lords Supper to them?</p>
               <p n="2">2. How doth he here confound the <hi>order</hi> and even make void the <hi>care</hi> of the Church in this matter.</p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>offer</hi> of it, we have already ſpoken; We aſſert there ought to be a <hi>previous profeſſion</hi> of acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation of the tender and offer by every ſoul, before the ſeal is adminiſtred to him, or elſe all <hi>order</hi> and <hi>purity</hi> will be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>And therefore we conclude this, that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119878:63"/>the Covenant belongs not to all, ſo as to have it ſealed unto them, unleſſe they firſt viſibly profeſſe to own it and accept of it before the Church; The former neglect of which cauſeth now a requiring of it of every perſon, or elſe godly men ſee not how Reformation will be attained to.</p>
               <p>But he produceth a Reply to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer anſwer; <hi>viz. What right doth this give him to the Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He anſwers with the main ſcope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Argument he produceth; As the <hi>Sacrament is a ſhewing forth of Chriſt with a tender of the Covenant in his bloud, there is an open, free, generall right to it for all that will come into Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We anſwer, The Sacrament is a ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of Chriſt with a tender, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to whom? To profeſſing beleevers that have been orderly received into the Church upon the Goſpel preached to them? And for ſuch as profeſſe before to <hi>come into Chriſt</hi> and ſubject to diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and whoſe converſations do not deny it, at leaſt profeſſing ſerious repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for the ſins they have lived in; which he grants to be the duty of every receiver, as to his own conſcience, in his
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119878:64"/>former anſwer, <hi>p.</hi> 50. But this we aſſert to be needfull to be profeſſed as to the ſatisfaction of the Church; Due reſpect and tenderneſſe being had to the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of any and to particulars.</p>
               <p>But he further diſtinguiſheth of a right of coming, <hi>There's a right of obligation and a right of priviledge; for the right of obligation in the Miniſters offer of Chriſt freely, and the Peoples receiving him on his own terms, I do avouch an univerſall right.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ,</hi> This is true in a ſenſe, ſo order be obſerved; If indeed a people <hi>receive Chriſt on his own terms</hi> (as he ſpeaks) and <hi>profeſſe</hi> to do ſo, then an obligation in the Miniſter to give the Sacrament; And the people being in their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, in ſome good meaſure ſatisfied, they came ſincerely before the Lord, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving examined their own hearts, there's a right of obligation upon them alſo to come.</p>
               <p>But if he mean an <hi>abſolute</hi> obligation of all to come, we deny it, unleſſe he is ahle to examine himielf, and doth ſo; and profeſſeth to the Church to take Chriſt on his own terms, and his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation doth not deny it.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:119878:64"/>
               <p>Next he brings in an humble ſoul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of his own unworthineſs, yet comes reſolving to give up himſelf to the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſay, An humble ſoul will come to his or her Miniſter, and profeſſe to doe ſo; And we wonder he ſhould put the caſe of humbled ſouls who are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited and encouraged; We here diſpute againſt him concerning the obſtinately ignorant, ſuperſtitious Formaliſts, and the prophane, who for the moſt part ſcorn at Reformation and Diſcipline; Of ſuch we ſay they have no right to come till humbled, and profeſſe to be ſo, nor is't the Miniſters duty, but ſin to receive them, ſpecially ſeeing he may prevent it if he will do his duty.</p>
               <p>The Text he uſeth further to prove an univerſall right to every Ordinance, is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.23. viz. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs that from one new Moon to another, and from one Sabbath to another, ſhall all fleſh come to worſhip before the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sure this is little for his purpoſe; We could anſwer, That many eminent Divines do underſtand this <hi>New Heavens and Earth</hi> in this Chapter of the <hi>New Hieruſalem</hi> in Heaven: But we inſiſt not
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119878:65"/>upon it: Grant it be meant of worſhip in the Church-Militant; What can be gathered from it but that <hi>All Fleſh,</hi> that is, ſome of all Nations ſhall ſubject to Goſpel-worſhip, (for we preſume he doth not underſtand it of every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall ſoul:) But ſure it ſhall be in Chriſts order, ſpecially in the later times, when Chriſt ſhall come as a Refiner of of his worſhip and people, yea, of the ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> in a ſpeciall manner, that they ſhall offer up pleaſant offerings to the Lord, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. That all ſorts of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons, no evidence of a change, ſhall come into the Lords Temple, and prophane the holy things of Chriſt, is not in the leaſt meaſure there meant, but the contrary; firſt orderly received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fellowſhip of the Church, and then, if not ſcandalous, the ſealing Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Supper.</p>
               <p>The ſixth Objection he would refell is, <hi>viz. The Sacrament is not a converting Ordinance; we preach to all to convert them, but we may adminiſter only to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate to confirm them;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he anſwers, <hi>That he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth Divines have uſually ſo ſtated it; Baptiſm for Initiation, the Supper for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119878:65"/>attributing our new birth to the former, &amp;c. Now</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I take a grant of the one to be a ſufficient medium to prove the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But Sir, you well know, that the Baptized in the Goſpel declared viſible converſion before they were baptized; <hi>He that beleeves</hi> (that is of grown years) <hi>ſhall be baptized;</hi> and the ſame reaſon of this Ordinance alſo in this reſpect. How he takes the conceſſion of one to be a grant of the other, we know not.</p>
               <p>Pag. 55. <hi>Aye but</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>'tis true of the ſame perſons, but as for others not yet converted, and humbly coming hither for converſion, there's no Scripture nor reaſon to the contrary, but he may be converted by it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We anſwer, To come humbly for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to this Ordinance, ſuppoſeth converſion begun, and ſo that ſoul comes for <hi>further</hi> converſion, which is one right uſe of this Ordinance; And whereas he ſaith, there's no Scripture nor reaſon to the contrary; We ſay there's both; 'Tis enough the Lord hath made no promiſe to it for converſion.</p>
               <p>And that it was alwaies uſed by ſuch who were ſuppoſed to be converted;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119878:66"/>The fellowſhip of the Saints; as we will preſently ſhew; and ſo ought it now only to be uſed.</p>
               <p>He repeats his former argument, that <hi>the Sacrament is a viſible word holding forth Chriſt and the Covenant to the ſight, therefore converting, as the Goſpel doing the ſame to the hearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Which thing is only aſſerted, but not proved, but by improper allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Centurions beleeving by ſeeing Chriſt only on the Croſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We anſwer, This was miraculous and extraordinary, not in the way of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, which is the thing in queſtion; With this Argument the Papiſts pleade for Crucifixes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Contemplation of the Creature-Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That reſts to be proved; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we deny not but any may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſee the celebration of the Supper, if that may do them good.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Sight of Miracles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Theſe were ordained by Chriſt to work faith, He hath not proved the Sacrament is ſo: Ordinarily <hi>Faith comes by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10.14. and not by <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:119878:66"/>'Tis not good arguing what Chriſt is <hi>able</hi> to do, to what he hath made no promiſe to do. And to proſtitute this holy Ordinance upon this account, and ſo to go out of Chriſts way and method (in reference to what he is <hi>able</hi> or may do) is not warrautable.</p>
               <p>This Argument was devis'd to chear up ſuch ſouls who are a little affected at the Lords Supper, who know little what converſion means; By this Argument known oppoſers of Truth and Purity ought to be invited to come for their converſion.</p>
               <p>Beſides, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humphreys</hi> nor any other, we humbly conceive, ought to admit or contrive any in the fellowſhip of his Church, but whom in a judgement of charity he ſuppoſeth converted, or hath no reaſon to conclude the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>But let us examine his Argument, which he cals all the world to anſwer, <hi>viz. To ſhew forth the death of Chriſt is the means of converſion, but the Sacrament is a ſhewing forth the death of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis true in the preaching of the Goſpel, the ſhewing forth of Chriſts
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119878:67"/>death is a means of converſion, but not in the Lords Supper, where 'tis only held forth, and ſhewed forth to ſuppoſed Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers; If it be converting in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the Apoſtles then did not uſe all the means of grace for converſion, They ſhould have celebrated the Supper at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sermon, and have bid the people, Come and eat, for here alſo the death of Chriſt is ſhewed forth to convert you, which he will never finde practiſed; If he ſay, The firſt Churches did every Lords day celebrate the Supper; That was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch as were eſteemed Saints, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready converted (as all within the Church are ſuppoſed in a charitable judgement) and in Chriſts order; Away with theſe Fallacies.</p>
               <p>But this he would prove further from the words of Juſtitution, <hi>Take and eat, [Take for ſuch as have not Chriſt, and eat for ſuch as have already received him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. A benè compoſitis ad malè diviſa;</hi> We take this very unſuitable to the parts of the Authour; We preſume a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction never heard of before; As it hath no appearance of ground, ſo we beleeve it not conſiderable with the weakeſt.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:119878:67"/>
               <p>If this had been the ſenſe, why had not Chriſt and the Apoſtles ſaid to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleevers <hi>Take,</hi> and to Beleevers <hi>Eat:</hi> This taking, is the putting forth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing faiuh before wrought; which we ſtill ſay this Ordinance ſuppoſeth, till he ſhall prove the contrary.</p>
               <p>He puts two or three caſes, <hi>A morall man coming and doing his beſt to prepare himſelf, and ſo comes, Do we think to ſuch a man this Ordinance is fruitleſſe? Then God help us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that is not enough to prove it is not, <hi>Yea</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall not his examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Prayers, Confeſſion, Meditation, be conducing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Briefly, Theſe are not like the acts of a morall man, Examination of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Faith, ſuppoſeth a beginning of both; And when Miniſters call upon morall men to examine themſelves in point of Repentance, the Spirit works by it if that ſoul really do it; yet we ſay, that if all theſe be but the acts of a moral man, there's no promiſe for his recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving good by this Ordinance; This is a good Argument to keep his rich Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in peace: <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.15, 16. ſhews it an old trade.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:119878:68"/>
               <p n="2">2. He puts the caſe of a <hi>poor humble Beleever, that comes hither to meet with Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We wonder at this caſe, the Queſtion being not about ſuch, being out of queſtion by all, but ſuch ought and are invited to come, to receive ſtrength and comfort by this Ordinance: ſo the two Diſciples of <hi>Emmaus,</hi> which he inſtanceth in, they were profeſſing Diſciples, and no queſtion, converted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though but weak.</p>
               <p>He brings in a reply of ſuch as oppoſe him in this; <hi>Although a man may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted at, it is not by the Sacrament, it is occaſionally, but not intentionally a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Ordinance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he Anſwers, <hi>This being unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably granted of our oppoſites, the matter is upon the point yielded, All</hi> It may be's, <hi>all occaſions muſt be taken for our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When godly men ſay a man <hi>may be</hi> converted <hi>at</hi> the Lords Supper, but not <hi>by</hi> it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We conceive they mean ſpecially by the Sermon or exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation before it, where all may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; And if he be then converted, it will be meet for him to ſtay till another
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119878:68"/>opportunity, that he may have a more ſpiritual diſcerning of that Ordinance: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> knows converſion uſually begins with conviction of ſinne, and though the ſeed of faith may be then ſown, yet it acts little at firſt; Chriſt not uſually giving a view of himſelf in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe at the firſt conviction; In ſuch a ſtrait a poor trembling ſoul will ſcarce venture to come.</p>
               <p>But granting him as much as he would have, his <hi>It may be,</hi> the point is not therefore yielded as he would perſwade his Reader and himſelf: The queſtion is not, as hath been alledged, What God <hi>can do,</hi> or what <hi>may be,</hi> but of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will of God, and the ordinary way of his diſpenſation of grace, which muſt be our rule to walk by.</p>
               <p>He would further back this argument with three conſiderations, <hi>wholly,</hi> as his confidence leads him, <hi>To root out this ſubtlety, which the ſpirit of errour hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This <hi>ſpirit of errour</hi> as he vainly boaſteth, will appear a ſpirit of truth and holineſs in the Lords ſervants, when his <hi>deluſions</hi> and <hi>profane aſſertions</hi> will ſtink in the noſtrils of the Saints, as it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119878:69"/>bleſſed be God, doth; The clouds of holy Witneſſes we might alleadge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, might cauſe him to bluſh at ſuch an arrogant paſſage.</p>
               <p>But,<note place="margin">Pag. 59.</note> ſaith he, <hi>The Sacraments and all Ordinances are primarily means of grace, it is but in a remote ſenſe they are means of converſion or confirmation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Now what a rooting out of this ſubtlety is here? Upon what Scripture doth he bottom his vain diſtinction? We ſay, All Ordinances are means of grace, but according to Chriſts order and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, The Word for <hi>converting</hi> grace, The Word and Sacrament alſo for <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming;</hi> and ſo they were ordained and ever uſed by Chriſt and the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Next, he diſtinguiſheth of converſion, 1. <hi>Outward, from heatheniſm to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt, we do not ſtand to ſay the Sacrament is ſuch a converting Ordinance.</hi> 2. <hi>True inward converſion wrought by the Word, not from any active power it hath in it ſelf, but</hi> per modum objecti, <hi>&amp;c. as an inſtrument uſed by the Spirit, ſo the Sacrament,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This is the ſubſtance of the ſecond.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> He intends by this to prove that if it may occaſionally, though not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:119878:69"/>convert, then all may come to it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To his diſtinction of converſion we Anſwer, That all that are converted by the Word, and ſo received into the Church, are ſuppoſed to be <hi>truly</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and ſo have this Ordinance ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to them; and therefore this deſtroyes all he hath ſaid in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: If it may be inſtrumental to inward effectual converſion, why may not his <hi>It may be,</hi> reach as well to Pagans, as thoſe Hypocrites in the Church? And to this he adds, <hi>We do not ſtand to ſay it ought, and let it be imagined,</hi> &amp;c. As if he had a minde to it; for indeed it will as naturally follow, if he anſwer, No, it ought not, becauſe Sacraments are only for ſuch as are within the Church; then ſure he more faſtens what he pretends in this reaſon to <hi>root out,</hi> for none are to be received or continued in the Church, but ſuch as are viſible Saints, ſuppoſed to be converted; as himſelf hath gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and ſo by conſequence 'tis not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a converting Ordinance, but for the Communion of Saints.</p>
               <p>And whereas he ſaith, <hi>The Spirit works by the Sacrament, as by the Word,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119878:70"/>by way of an inſtrument:</hi> and ſo if the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament do occaſionally convert, 'tis enough; It hath been anſwered, that this converſion <hi>at</hi> the Sacrament, which ſome godly men aſſert, is meant, not preciſely of the Sacrament, but of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Preaching, Exhortation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Beſidcs the word is intentionally, by the reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed will of God, an inſtrument of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and ſo an Inſtitution of Chriſt, but this of the Sacrament is not yet, nor we verily beleeve ever will, be proved to be ſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He follows this, as if he had gained much by this conceſſion of <hi>Occaſionally converting,</hi> wherein we fear he wilfully miſtakes godly men; who ever mean it only of the concomitant duties at it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo he frames to himſelf a diſtinction of <hi>principall and ſubordinate intention of converſion; The Sacrament hath a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate intention,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But, Sir, who grants you this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that are contrary to your judgement, <hi>That the Sacrament hath a ſubordinate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of converſion,</hi> &amp;c. We know of none ſuch who ſpeak of it, as occaſional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converting do not imply it, <hi>occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> and <hi>intentionally</hi> are not ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119878:70"/>but diſtinct; beſides, Godly men, as hath been ſhew'd, do not ſpeak of the Sacrament <hi>preciſely,</hi> when they ſo ſpeak; yet how the man pleaſeth himſelf with his own creature and fancy, and laughs upon it exceedingly! <hi>p.</hi> 61, 62.</p>
               <p>He further urgeth, <hi>Prayer is not ſo primarily converting, therefore by this rule prayer may alſo be exeluded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We need anſwer no further to this, he frames a ſhadow and fights a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; He takes that granted to him, which no judicious Divine we know al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows him: We ſay Prayer is ſubordinat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converting, but we deny and leave him to prove, <hi>ad graecas Calendas,</hi> that the Sacrament is. We might here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforce M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Gileſpyes</hi> twenty Arguments to prove the Sacrament not converting, which he will anſwer at the ſame time; but we intend briefneſs.</p>
               <p>The next he Anſwers to is, <hi>But unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate men are dead in ſin, ſhall we give bread to the dead? men muſt be firſt born, living, before they can feed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he Anſwers, <hi>If we could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any ſuch bread as would fetch life in a dead man, we would give it him; Now, ſaies Chriſt,</hi> Joh. 6.33. <hi>I am the bread of life,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:119878:71"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is to beg the queſtion, That the Sacrameut is ordain'd to fetch life in a dead man; yea, ſaith he, <hi>Chriſt is the Bread of Life,</hi> Here he gratifies the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts (as well as the poor, ignorant, and prophane people of the Nation) who underſtand that <hi>Bread</hi> in <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. to be of Sacramentall bread, which ſound Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſtill oppoſe; Chriſt as offered in the Sacrament is not Bread to beget life, his bare aſſertion doth not prove it; His parallell between <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> and <hi>Calix vitae,</hi> is not worth notice; Or if it were, we beleeve M. <hi>Humphreys</hi> doth not know of any <hi>Aqua vitae</hi> that will beget life in a dead man, though it may revive where life is remaining. The ſame we ſay of the <hi>Cup</hi> as an ordained means where Chriſt is offered.</p>
               <p>As to the matter of <hi>Judas</hi> which he again replys to, we have ſpoken alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; And we ſhould be too tedious to urge all, What godly men have ſaid for <hi>Judas</hi> not receiving the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="1">1. How unlikely it is that the Lord ſhould ſay to <hi>Judas</hi> (whom he cals the Son of Perdition, and a devil) This is <hi>my body which was broken for thee,</hi> and <hi>this is my bloud which was ſhed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119878:71"/>of thy ſins,</hi> and <hi>Thou ſhalt drink with me in my Fathers Kingdom;</hi> All which he ſpake to <hi>Judas</hi> as to the reſt, if he were one.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But ſhould we grant he ate, ſure M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humphreys</hi> gains little to his cauſe; <hi>Judas</hi> was not yet convinced before the Church of the fact, having not yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it; If he ſhould have been kept off upon the fear that he might commit it, <hi>Peter</hi> might have been as well kept off as he, for he in Chriſts knowledge was to commit a ſcandalous offence alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither will it in the leaſt meaſure warrant the admitting of all ſorts now; <hi>Judas</hi> was a perſon that preached and profeſſed Chriſt, and for a time forſook the world to follow him, was no ſcoffer or reviler at the power of godlineſſe, and had given no open ſcandall to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; We wiſh it could be ſaid ſo of all ſuch as cry for Free Admiſſion upon this ground.</p>
               <p>The eighth Objection he would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to, is, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy Receivers are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſts bloud, and eat their damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, therefore we muſt not allow a Free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this he anſwers, 1. <hi>As to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119878:72"/>part.</hi> 2. <hi>As to the Receivers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the Churches part, this cannot any way concern them. There is a generall Command,</hi> Do this, <hi>Every man is to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf, and he receives damnation</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to himſelf, they receive not ours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. His <hi>verily beleeve</hi> doth not prove it doth not concern the Church; The Church is concern'd to keep her ſelf from <hi>pollution and ruine,</hi> both which are brought upon it by this vile practiſe; If the Church, both Officers and Members, do not their utmoſt to prevent a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly impenitent ſinner from coming to this Ordinance, they are guilty of his ſin, as hath been proved; We are (ſaith <hi>Zanchy</hi>) violaters of charity and guilty of iniquity,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. p. <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> to ſuffer men to damn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Sacrament, which we might ſuſpend from them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such a levity is the way to bring upon Miniſters the puniſhment of <hi>Eli,</hi> the ſin being much like it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is it <hi>nothing</hi> to a Miniſter to ſee a people he is ſent to ſave, in Gods hand, eating and drinking damnation to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> proteſted, he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give his body to a Murderer, then the Sacrament to a ſcandalous perſon;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119878:72"/>And <hi>Calvin,</hi> that he would rather put his hand into the fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to his reaſon, ſaith he, <hi>There is a generall command, Do this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We wonder he will ſo inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately call it a <hi>generall</hi> command, when he knows 'twas ſpoken only to the 12. that ate with him.</p>
               <p>Oh but ſaith he, <hi>Let him examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and he damns himſelf, not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It doth not follow, that becauſe every perſon coming is bound to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf, therefore no body elſe is, Though he receives damnation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet it doth not thence follow, that others have not a hand in forwarding his damnation, if they do not their duty to prevent it; Though a man murdering himſelf is chiefly guilty of the fact, yet it follows not but thoſe are in a meaſure guilty who prevent him not when 'tis in their power; Every man ſhall give an account of himſelf to God, <hi>yet their bloud will I require at thy hands,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>Why ſhould God ſay, <hi>Be ready to give an account of the hope that is in thee,</hi> if no body have power to require it of him?</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:119878:73"/>
               <p>We verlly beleeve M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doth not conceive thoſe words of ſelf-examining ſpoken <hi>excluſively;</hi> who doubts (unleſſe ſuch as are prophane ſcorners) but that a Miniſter is to take all occaſions to examine the people he is ſent to, for their further edification, ſpecially when they have been lull'd in ignorance before? 'Tis indeed a <hi>looſe</hi> and <hi>prophane</hi> aſſertion, That poor ignorant creatures and prophane wretches muſt come in a cuſtomary way to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chriſt, to their own damnation, without repentance; And yet the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitters no way, no, <hi>not any way,</hi> as he maintaineth, concerned in it.</p>
               <p>'Tis the note of a godly minde to urge Scripture to ſuch ends for which God ordained them, as this, to preſſe ſelf-examination, not as to make void all private reproof, admonition, and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, contrary to other Scriptures; Wo to the Land if all were of this looſe judgement; Let all people damn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at pleaſure by Sacraments, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns no body, neither Miniſters nor people.</p>
               <p>What godly man doth not ſee but this ſhift is put into the head of carnall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119878:73"/>by the devil and his factors; to keep them in ſecurity, they never intending to examine themſelves, nor are indeed able, and ſo will not ſuffer any man elſe to do it; It concerns none but himſelf, ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This ſelf-examination may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to others judgement of them, <hi>viz.</hi> That though the Elders of <hi>Corinth</hi> did unduly admit them, they were not to reſt on their judgement of them, but to examine <hi>themſelves;</hi> which only can prevent that judgement of God ſpoken of 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11.31. And the <hi>judging of themſelvos</hi> there may alſo referre to the Churches judging, as good Authors conceive.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If Perſons have been duly received and confirm'd into the Church, then 'tis ſuppoſed they give ſufficient ſatisfaction in point of knowledge, and ſo that part of examination by the Elderſhip or Church, which is now called for in our times, as to <hi>knowledge,</hi> would ceaſe; But it is the ignorance of people is now moſt complained of, and ſo examination in this reſpect more required, becauſe there hath been ſufficient means of knowledge but in few places.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:119878:74"/>
               <p>But M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> would prevent what we have anſwered by fore-ſtalling the Objection, <hi>If another ſhould be taking a Cup of poyſon, ſhall not we be partakers of his bloud if we do not hinder or forbid him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But alas how poorly he wipes it of? What a rattle hath he got to ſtill conſcience?</p>
               <p>Saith he, <hi>We have no</hi> quùm poſſit, <hi>that is, no power to hinder,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> What if he had?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Doth he not abſolutely pleade that all are to come, and it <hi>concerns</hi> no body, <hi>no way,</hi> to keep them off?</p>
               <p n="2">2. But ſuppoſe he would, this will not ſerve the turn; To whom are the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven left, to keep off, and caſt out primarily, but to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church? If your people will not ſubmit to diſcipline, to Chriſts yoke, they are not fit for Sacraments; In a word, That Goſpel which declares their receiving to be a damnable ſin, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns all miniſteriall care to prevent ſin, and ſave mens ſouls, doth <hi>eo ipſo,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you to put them back, and to put your Church into Chriſts order that you may do it; No Goſpel-practiſe puts a
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119878:74"/>neceſſity upon any man to ſin.</p>
               <p>Next, He wonders <hi>Any religious man ſhould call the Sacrament a cup of poyſon ſeeing it is a cup of bleſſing: If it prove death to any, 'tis ſinne takes an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sir, What religious man doth call it a Cup of poyſon, in any other ſenſe then you your ſelf do, that is, as ſin taking occaſion makes it ſo? Why will you gratifie men of corrupt mindes with ſuch <hi>forgeries,</hi> to make them hate their Miniſters more?</p>
               <p>He re-enforceth his conſtant Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>God is able to make it a cup of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That's not the Query what God is <hi>able</hi> to do (as hath been anſwered) but what God hath <hi>ordain'd</hi> for ſuch and ſuch an end, and what he hath <hi>promis'd</hi> to do; And ſo he hath not <hi>ordain'd</hi> nor <hi>promis'd</hi> this Sacrament to be a Cup of bleſſing to an unbeleever, or the worſt, as he ſtiles it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us act</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with charïtable thoughts, and leave the ſucceſſe to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But Sir, you muſt have <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> for your charity; That profane ignorant perſons are Chriſts Diſciples, is
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:119878:75"/>a <hi>groundleſſe</hi> charity; Beſides, what do you talk of charity in your apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all that come, ſeeing you aſſert all are to come whether converted or not converted, and the Miniſter nor Church is not to conſider of it?</p>
               <p>His compariſon between Preaching the Word and adminiſtring the Sacrament, hath been refelled; 'Tis true <hi>Paul</hi> preacht in every place, though the Word was a ſavour of death to ſome; but Sir, he did not adminiſter the Supper in every place, but only to profeſſing Saints <hi>joyned</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel; And to adminiſter it to others is not to make this Ordinance a <hi>ſweet ſavour,</hi> but a loathing to the zealous and holy God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He comes to the Receivers part, leſſening the unworthy Receivers ſin, when 'twere his duty to be aggravating and bewailing it: he ſaith,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is a double duty, A Principall, Do this; An Acceſſory, Examine; If he fails in examining himſelf, and is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, he is to come,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. He well enough knows, but that he would blinde poor ſouls, That <hi>Do this</hi> was ſpoken to Diſciples of Chriſts
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119878:75"/>Family, not to all; that as oft as they <hi>do</hi> it, they do it in remembrance of Chriſts death, Doth it follow therefore that every one is to do it? A Maſter of a Feaſt bids all at his Table eat, all that are preſent, doth he therefore bid all the Town eat?</p>
               <p n="2">2. That which he cals an <hi>acceſſory du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> let a man <hi>Examine,</hi> is the ground of his coming, A limitation of the duty, without which none ought to come; but he urgeth further,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thoſe dreadfull expreſſions of being guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſts bloud, and eating damnation, are not to affright any from coming,</hi> &amp;c. No? Not any man? What not an Idolater? an inceſtuous perſon, a hater of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with whom he pretends to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate as one body? Not one that keeps a Brothell-houſe, nor a witch, nor a revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sir, In this your prophane Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes are aſhamed of you; They will tell you this is larger then 'twas in their old free prophane daies; Then the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter was us'd to pronounce by way of threatning, <hi>If any of you he a Blaſphemer of God, a hinderer or ſlanderer of his Word, an Adulterer, or be in malice or envy, or in any other grievous crime, bewail your
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119878:76"/>ſin, and come not to this holy Table;</hi> Mark it Reader, <hi>Bewail it,</hi> and <hi>Come not:</hi> but ſaith the Patron of thy ſin M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H. However come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, In earneſt, Do you conceive thoſe dreadfull judgements threatned are not to affright prophane perſons? When a prophane perſon hears grievous judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threatned to ſuch a practice, ought not that perſon to refrain it? <hi>No,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>he ought to prepare himſelf;</hi> That's true, but the Queſtion is, If he finde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not prepared, yet hearing ſuch judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threatned, Whether he ought to come, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> ſaith, <hi>He dare not ſay he ought not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What's this but to encourage poor creatures to ruſh boldly upon ſinne and judgement, which the body of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation have long done in a moſt abominable manner?</p>
               <p>And yet now they muſt be clapt on the back for it, and they are taught by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> they ought to come however, and 'tis the Miniſters duty to receive them; How little hath he conſidered how the people of this Nation are hardened by cuſtome to come prophanely? And let Miniſters pronounce a thouſand judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119878:76"/>to unworthy coming, yet it hath been their cuſtome to come, to have a communion and new clothes, and be merry at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> Therefore have it they will, or the Miniſter ſhall rue it if it be in their power; ſpecially ſince 'tis duty to come though drunk in that moment; as <hi>Free Admiſſion</hi> alloweth.</p>
               <p>His aſſertion is backt with three Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. He diſtinguiſheth between the <hi>Act of receiving and the unworthineſſe of it, the Act is good, though the manner be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> So may the Act of murder be ſaid to be good, as 'tis an action, or any other vile action, becauſe it hath being, and ſo good in a Metaphyficall ſenſe, which we will not puzzle our Reader with, ſpeaking chiefly to the deceived people; Know Reader, the Scripture cals it damnable ſin, to come unworthily, and be not flattered into ſin, by ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound niceties; There's no morall good in the coming, God hates thee in thy coming, thou bring'ſt greater ſin upon thy ſoul if thou comeſt unworthily. Ah how are poor ignorant ſouls ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by this reaſon? they beleeve there's
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119878:77"/>
                  <hi>ſome good,</hi> and they do ſome good in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and this makes amends for much prophaneſſe.</p>
               <p>He may indeed ſay as much for the fouleſt ſin in the world, T he act is good, as it hath being, but the ſinne is in the manner; Eating and drinking ſimply conſidered at the Sacrament is not ſin, but ignorance and unworthineſſe makes it ſo.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>There's unworthineſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Perſon if he do not come,</hi> p. 71.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But not ſo great; To be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and come in that unworthineſſe to a holy action (which the Word ſtiles damnable) is an aggravation of it, and a greater ſin, and an abominable moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of God and defiling his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
               <p>His ſecond Query is, <hi>Whether recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Sacrament be otherwiſe damnable then hearing and praying, which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes is not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though to pray and hear in a carnall manner be great ſins, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe of Receiving is greater; which thoſe dreadfull Expreſſions in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. do witneſſe; beſide there lie abſolute commands upon every one to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119878:77"/>
                  <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>pray,</hi> Rev. 13.9. <hi>If any man have an ear to hear let him hear,</hi> Jer. 10.25. The action of receiving is of a more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and holy nature, and the ſin of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning it greater: So that if a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon refrains to come, he ſinnes leſſe; though this doth not at all excuſe his continuing in prophaneſſe.</p>
               <p>But he helps himſelf with a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby he pretends to ſalve all: <hi>There's a preſumptuous prophane way of coming to an Ordinance, or a Chriſtian co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in conformity to God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here's a skinning ſoul-flattering plaiſter for the Enemies of Reformation; It's a ſweet bit for the devil to keep up rotten formality: Sir, Doth not he come in a prophane preſumptuous way, who comes but in an outward Conformity? Doth not the moſt prophane wretch do ſo? and thinks he doth enough, and covers many ſins by it, he will tell you he comes in a conformity to Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; How many Scriptures might we give him, and we preſume not unknown to him, where the Lord expreſſeth his abhorrency of ſuch worſhip; See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.11. &amp; 66.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Chapt.</hi> &amp;c. The people there came before God as his
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:119878:78"/>people, in ſuch waies of worſhip as he appointed; But they came but in an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conformity, therefore (ſaith the Lord) <hi>'tis an abomination to me, an ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, my ſoul hateth it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Therefore this is a diſtinction abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Lord; whoever comes in a meer outward conformity, comes in a preſumptuous prophane way.</p>
               <p>His third Query, <hi>Whether an unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man conceiving himſelf not worthy, muſt never come to the Sacrament,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He anſwers, <hi>Herein my thoughts are apt to run comparatively on the word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> An unregenerate perſon finding himſelf ſuch, is not, as ſuch, to come, 'twas not ordained for his good; Not to ſow the firſt ſeed of his new birth, but to ſtrengthen it; 2. We deny to be the ſame reaſon of coming to the Word and Sacrament, for though he hath been and is an unworthy hearer, yet he is to go, becauſe the Word preached is ordained for converſion, but not the Sacrament, which is for the Communion of Saints; whereas he ſaith, <hi>'tis a means of grace,</hi> 'tis a fallacy, 'tis not a means of the firſt grace.</p>
               <p>He ſpeaks in the cloſe of a ſoul laying
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:119878:78"/>to heart the horrour of his ſinne in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty of Chriſts Bloud, and ſo to come.</p>
               <p>This is true, and granted, If he doth lay it to heart, and profeſſe to do ſo, then the Church doth encourage him to come.</p>
               <p>But we ſay, This horrour of his ſin is wrought by the preaching of the Word, not by the Act of receiving; And we beleeve a ſoul made ſenſible of this dreadfull guilt in his frequent former co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings, will tremble to come at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, though he is afterwards upon the profeſſion of his ſin to be encouraged; 'twill not hurt him to lie under theſe humblings; yea, if a poor creature ſhall doubt of his regeneration, and ſo open his condition to the Miniſter or the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people, he is to be encouraged if any appearance of regeneration in a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble judgement be upon him.</p>
               <p>But ſaith he: <hi>If coming unworthily makes a man guilty of Chriſts bloud, how much more ſhall open refuſing it, that tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples upon it in this Ordinance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Briefly, By continuing in ſinne and coming to this Ordinance, there's a more abominable trampling under foot
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:119878:79"/>the bloud of Chriſt, becauſe they make it an unclean thing, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in their uncleanneſſe, and ſo tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling upon and deſpiſing the ends of Chriſts bloud, purity and holineſſe; It matters not which is preciſely the greater ſin, 'tis enough to make a prophane wretch to tremble, that in coming <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily</hi> he becomes guilty of the Lords bloud, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So to make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain.</p>
               <p>The ninth Objection againſt his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he brings on to anſwer, is, <hi>The Ordinance is polluted if all be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He grants it; <hi>To the unworthy Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, to whom all things are unclean, but not to the Admitters unleſſe the unworthy are convicted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But Sir, What if the Miniſter and the reſt of the Admitters do not their duty to convict an ignorant or a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon, but ſuffer him to come; When they have power and command from Chriſt, as they are a Church, to do ſo, is it not then both Miniſters and Peoples ſin? We dare averre, the Lord will require it of them without their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or elſe <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. ſtands for a
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:119878:79"/>blank, and Chriſt will never take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it.</p>
               <p>But though this duty be not perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, yet they may come fearleſly, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> conceives, <hi>No more ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaith he, then if the cloth be not clean enough on the table.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſ. <hi>Satis profanè,</hi> an expreſſion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy a Chriſtian (that we may not flatter him) and an abhorring to the Lords people: That a godly ſoul ſeeing a company of profane wretches, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to godlineſs (as what Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on abounds not with ſuch?) come to this holy myſtery, and though he doth not his duty by private admonition and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring their conviction, yet he is no more to be troubled to ſee the blood of his Saviour made an unclean thing, then for an unclean cloth.</p>
               <p>Now Reader, thou feeſt this Author in his own ſhape: His profane Proſelytes ſure will ſay he hath ſtretcht conſcience a little too much for them here.</p>
               <p>But he will venture to prove it: <hi>In the Law,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>there was a diſtinction of the clean and unclean, which otherwiſe would defile their Saorifices, and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; But no ſuch thing now in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:119878:80"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is the ſubſtance of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; We Reply; It hath been already proved by us, that the Jews were kept off from the Sacrifices and Paſſeover, as well for Moral uncleanneſs, as Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial,<note place="margin">Joh. 9.22. &amp; 12.42. Ezra 10.11.</note> and that the Ceremoniall unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was a type of the uncleanneſs of ſin under the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Beſides, Was God ſo zealous of his worſhip, and the prophaning of it then, that unclean perſons were to be cut off, and is there no profaning the holy my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Lord Jeſus now? Nor no care to be taken that unclean perſons be not ſuffered to defile them? What a curſed proſtitution of the holy things of God is this? But, ſaith he,
<q>There is nothing unclean to us now.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Aye but there are things that are too holy for the unclean now, as this holy myſtery is.</p>
               <p>But to prove there is nothing unclean now, he urgeth <hi>Ro.</hi> 14.14. <hi>I know I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there is nothing unclean of it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sir, you know well enough that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks there of meats, to the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the weak Jews, who took ſome meats ſtill to be accounted unclean under the Goſpel; But now he convinceth
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:119878:80"/>them ther's nothing, <hi>no meat</hi> to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>unclean.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What's this to his purpoſe to prove there is no polluting the holy Ordinance of the Lords Supper? unleſſe he will make no difference between common meat, and the Lords Supper; which the truth is, his Free Admiſſion doth not; This is his argument:</p>
               <p>No meat is now unclean, legall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs being taken off, therefore all may come to the Lords Supper; no pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting of it, or at it.</p>
               <p>That of <hi>Peters</hi> viſion is like it; Jews and Gentiles are to have the Goſpel preached, therefore no man is defiled by communicating with a wicked perſon, though he take no care for the preventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him.</p>
               <p>He goes on and urgeth, <hi>Now in the Goſpel All's free, we are to have free Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But, Sir, In Chriſts way, The Goſpel preached freely to all, but the ſeals of it to profeſſing Saints.</p>
               <p>He breaks off with a ſharp exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the godly Miniſters and people, thus; <hi>My Brethren, there are ſome touches of the Law and ſuperſtition on you,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:119878:81"/>you know what a ſacred thing was made of the Communion Table when the rayl was about it; Now I pray think how you refine and ſpiritualize your old ſuperſtition, by putting a ſpiritual rayl about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when you debarre poor ſinners for coming hither: Let us take heed, there will be ſomething of the Phariſee in theſe ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual proud hearts of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Lord rebuke him for this cenſorious ſarcaſm; We look upon this diſcovery as the juſt hand of God upon him.</p>
               <p>Tis the language of the formall, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm, profane Miniſters and people againſt the godly party; Oh, ſay they, this is their ſpiritual pride and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiſme: This paſſage is nuts for them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis very baſe (to ſay no more) for a Miniſter to caſt ſuch dirt upon the fair unblemiſht memories of ſelf-denying Saints, who are now fallen aſleep in the Lord; who ſuffered deprivations, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, impriſonments, upon this very ſcore chiefly, that they would not adminiſter Sacraments to all: And now, ſaith this Pamphleter, as their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors did, 'Twas their ſpiritual pride; As they damnd the power of Religion to be
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:119878:81"/>ſuch, and as the Lukewarm, Anti-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming party do: Yea doth he not caſt this upon the Wiſdom of Parliament, the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines, yea all the moſt Learned and Godly Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers both Antient and Modern, as ever the Church of Chriſt hath been bleſt with: This cenſorious man hath written upon them all, <hi>Phariſaiſm,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Pride;</hi> becauſe every mans conſcience is not ſo eaſie, large, and wide as his own, about the ſanctifying the Lords Name in this Ordinance.</p>
               <p>Oh but ſaith he, <hi>'Tis ſuperſtition too, as bad as the rayl about the Communion Table.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The truth is, he is fitter to be admoniſht, to go weep and howl in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate all his daies, for this and other (ſuch) curſed aſſertions, then to have an anſwer given to them; were not thouſands of ſouls even like to periſh and be harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſin by them? Sir, Doth that Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous practice of erecting Altars, and railing them about as holy, run parallel with the practice of a conſcientious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, who trembleth that poor ſouls ſhould eat damnation, and he not labour to prevent it? And as to your rayl, The
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:119878:82"/>Diſcipline of Chriſts Churches was wont to be ſtiled the rayl or fence of them, to preſerve this holy Ordinance from pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: If you get not ſuch a rayl Chriſt may root out you and your Church (ſuch as it is) ere you are aware.</p>
               <p>Sir, Inſtead of this Caveat to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters who plead for and practice Reformation in the uſe of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; May you tremble at a ſpirit of Apoſtacy from it, which begins ſadly to ſteal upon too too many who have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly with great zeal contended for it, and that you nor they be not given up of God to greater deluſions and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations then theſe.</p>
               <p>A little to ſalve the buſineſſe, he brings in the reply of the godly to his former argument, <hi>But are we not faulty and partake of other mens ſinnes if we do not our beſt to have the leaven purged out,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He Anſwers,<note place="margin">Pag. 79.</note> 
                  <hi>There are ſeveral duties of a Chriſtian, To pray, receive, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his, to rebuke the faulty, to tell the Church, if it be in a capacity: if we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect we are guilty, and defiled; What then? we muſt labour after a</hi> Church-Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:119878:82"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is not this to grant in effect what we contend for, That 'tis every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants ſin if he do not admoniſh a perſon coming prophanely to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and he becomes guilty if he neglect it? If rebuking the faulty as to all ſin, be a duty, then 'tis ſo in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; for he that hinders not another from ſin according to his <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> is guilty of that ſin, and the <hi>duty</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> hath confeſt, yea all <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, commenders, conſentors, connivers, councellors, concealers, excuſers of other mens ſins,</hi> are guilty of them, of which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> is one, and all that plead for Free Admiſſion.</p>
               <p>He limits the duty of <hi>telling the Church,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>If the Church be in a capacity to hear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then 'tis granted the Church ought to be in a <hi>capacity</hi> to hear: If he means by this capacity, A Church enjoying all Officers, whoſe fault is it that you have them not? Who is to chooſe them but your Church? If they be not fit to chooſe they are not fit for Sacraments, as hath been ſhewed, we mean as to a good part of them; but we conceive the Church it ſelf, as diſtinguiſht from its
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:119878:83"/>Officers, is in a <hi>capacity</hi> to hear, and ought to be told by a conſcientious mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or elſe he will not quit the guilt mentioned, ſay M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> what he will.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He grants we ſhould labour after a <hi>Church-eſtabliſhment:</hi> This we truſt will juſtifie our practiſe, in doing our duties in it (by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) and ſo will ſtop the mouths of thoſe of his minde againſt our practice, which, with our ſelves, we cannot ſee, after much ſeeking the Lord for directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how it can be attained to, but by calling upon ſuch as will ſubmit to the Diſcipline of <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. with us, and ſo being joyned together, and chooſing Officers, there ariſeth a <hi>Church-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by the power of the Goſpel: We wiſh M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> had ſpent his time and paper he beſtowed in maintaining pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous <hi>Free Admiſſion,</hi> in ſtirring up Miniſters to preſs on to ſuch a <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhment,</hi> and not in hardning peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſin and ignorance.</p>
               <p>But he further urgeth, <hi>Muſt we in the mean while have no Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Better ſure, after a patient wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon ſouls for embracing the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:119878:83"/>to begin with Church-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then to adminiſter the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, without ſo much diſhonour to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and endangering of ſouls, in promiſcuous admiſſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Further, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> by his <hi>mean while,</hi> implies that in an exigency there ought to be Free Admiſſion, rather then no Sacraments: Though we conceive that doth not abſolutely take away the guilt, yet we could wiſh that he had ſo ſtated the queſtion, and not to preſs his Free Admiſſion <hi>abſolutely</hi> upon Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and people, and that 'tis their ſin not to allow it.</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>The neglect of this duty of admonition, is the ſin by it ſelf, the coming is our duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Here is a fine nicety to skin over a ſin: Sir, If a Godly man do not admoniſh a wicked man coming, that ſo he may profeſs his repentance to the Church, or be kept off, ſuch a one comes to the Sacrament with guilt upon him, for he hath not performed a concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant duty in coming; and ſo his want of admonition is a ſin in reference to his coming.</p>
               <p>Aye but ſaith he, <hi>Becauſe the leaven
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:119878:84"/>is not purged out, muſt there be no lump?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, but ſuch a lump as is totally lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened and defiled for want of this duty, and therefore ought to become a new lump, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</p>
               <p>The next reply brought againſt his argument is, <hi>Are not all ignorant and ſcandalous perſons ſwine and dogs, to be rejected, and ſo kept off from pearls,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He anſwers, I dare not ſay, though I ſee what intereſt lies at ſtake, which may ſoon fancy a Chriſtian conveniency into a divine neceſſity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What though <hi>you</hi> dare not ſay ſo? 'tis enough that Jeſus Chriſt himſelf ſaith ſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. he cals them dogs, and commands that holy things be not given them, and this of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is to be eſteemed the holieſt. What <hi>Intereſt</hi> he means we do not rightly know; but we well know Free Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtands well with the intereſt of carnal eaſe, friendſhip of ungodly men, and profit; but keeping off doth not.</p>
               <p>And Sir, 'tis not only Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency to keep off ſuch, but a <hi>poſitive command</hi> of Chriſt in that Scripture. To his five reaſons,</p>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:119878:84"/>
               <p n="1">1. We deny your proofs to aſſure the contrary, 'tis <hi>gratis dictum,</hi> as we hope is cleared.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He placeth a great diſtance between unfitneſs to come unto the Sacrament, and being excluded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If a perſon be not fit to come, and his unfitneſs viſible, he ought to be excluded, and ſo kept from ſin: Though you put a great diſtance between them, they ought to go together.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He urgeth, <hi>The keeping off any can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be pretended to in our un- Elder'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This we beleeve gave the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to this Diſcourſe; and upon this ſcore, we fear many go on <hi>to ſin againſt light:</hi> But doth not this imply that if Congregations were Elderd then there ought to be keeping off, and ſo Free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion vaniſheth, and not to be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily preſt?</p>
               <p n="2">2. But, Sir, ſtill whoſe fault is it that theſe are not Elderd Congregations? ſure the Miniſters and Churches own, as hath been alledged: Who are to chooſe the Elders? certainly the Church; or let it be proved the contrary; But the <hi>major</hi> part, you will ſay, is corrupt and not fit
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:119878:85"/>to chooſe? Then ſure not fit to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſealing Ordinances, as hath been hinted. People that fear the Lord can diſcern of ſuch perſons who are moſt godly, grave, and wiſe, and ſo fitted for Church-Officers.</p>
               <p>This is a moſt generally received truth, That every particular Congregation hath power in it ſelf to reform it ſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what ſhall be practicable by them.</p>
               <p>There is nothing alledged againſt this but the expectation of a <hi>Civil ſanction;</hi> what weight or authority will that adde to Chriſts Ordinance? which obligeth the conſcience without humane autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; ſuch a ſanction or humane law may make men hypocritically ſubmit, but will not adde to <hi>real</hi> Reformation. <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit,</hi> ſaith the Lord by the Prophet, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.6. We have ſpoke to this in the Preface: We will take leave to alledge what D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Jewell</hi> in his Epiſtle concerning the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> annexed in the cloſe of that Hiſtory; which is applicable to the preſent caſe: Miniſters alleadging there can be no Church-Reformation, without a Civil ſanction and Law from
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:119878:85"/>Authority, though they protect godly men in their duty.</p>
               <p>The Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> alleadged, There was no Reformation to be attempted in <hi>England</hi> without a General Councel; To which the Doctor replies, <hi>pag.</hi> 858. <hi>Is it not lawfull for any of us to beleeve in Chriſt, to profeſſe the Goſpel, to ſerve God aright, to fly ſuperſtition and Idolatry, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they will be pleaſed to give us leave? &amp;c.</hi> In the following page, <hi>Muſt we therefore ſit idle, expecting how theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will handle the matter? Muſt we hold our hands together and do nothing?</hi> Further, <hi>I will require, ſaith the Lord, their blood at thy hands: If any ſhall put his hand to the plough and look back, and be ſolicitous what others think, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the authority of a General Councel, and hide the Lords treaſure, in the mean while he ſhall hear this, Oh evil and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſervant, take him away and caſt him into utter darkneſſe. Suffer, ſaith Chriſt, the dead to bury the dead, but follow thou me. In humane Counſels it is the part of a wiſe man to expect the judgment and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of men, but in matters divine, Gods Word is all in all, the which ſo ſoon as a godly man hath received, he preſently yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:119878:86"/>and ſubmitteth himſelf, he is not wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering nor expecting others: He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth that he is not bound to give ear to the Pope or Councel, but to the will of God, whoſe voice is to be obeyed though all men ſay nay. The Prophet</hi> Elias <hi>preſently obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gods voice, though he thought he was alone.</hi> Abraham <hi>being warned of God went out of</hi> Chaldea. Lot <hi>went out of</hi> Sodom, &amp;c. <hi>Go, ſaith the Angel, out of the midſt of her, and partake not of her ſins, leaſt you taſt of her plagues: He ſaith not, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a Synod of Biſhops. If at the firſt Chriſt and his Apoſtles had ſtayd for a Councell, when had their ſound gone up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Lands?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Pag. 860. <hi>For we know that the Spirit of God is tied neither to places nor to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of men. Tell it to the Church, ſaith Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">☞</note> 
                  <hi>not to the whole Church ſpread over the whole world, but to a particular, which may eaſily meet in one place: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſaith he, two or three ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in my Name, there am I in the midſt of them: When</hi> Paul <hi>would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Churches of the Corinthians and of the Galatians, he did not command them to expect a General Councel, but only wrote unto them, that what errour ſoever or
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:119878:86"/>vice was among them,</hi> themſelves <hi>ſhould preſently cut it off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now we humbly conceive what this Reverend Authour ſaith of a General Councel, is in this caſe applicable to Magiſtrates; As the Churches of <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Galatia</hi> were not to ſtay for a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, as to the Reforming their Churches, ſo neither for an Edict from the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; The Lord will require the blood of ſuch as periſh for want of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, at <hi>our</hi> hands. In matters divine, ſaith he, Gods Word muſt be obeyed, though <hi>All men ſay nay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſay ſome, If the Magiſtrate would give us authority, we would ſet about this practice; Sure this will not ſerve the turn before the bar of the Lord, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it may quiet conſcience for a time. We verily beleeve, did we look more to Chriſt, and leſſe to men, the Goſpel would have its courſe more freely.</p>
               <p>But to return to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Men may be Dogs and Swine either in the courſe of their life, or in the publique e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of the Church, we look to them as they are in the Churches eſteem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Briefly, This is but a rotten <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve;</hi> As if 'twere to be ſatisfaction e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:119878:87"/>to a godly Miniſter, what a company of ignorant and carnall peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall think one of another; ſay they, We were all us'd to come at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> why be we not all fit now?</p>
               <p n="2">2, If by the Church he mean the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, it doth not come to his caſe; But were it ſo, that a known ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould be otherwiſe eſteem'd by them, yet the Miniſter having uſed all other waies of remedy, be is not to ſin from other mens judgements.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Saith he, <hi>To ſpeak particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ignorant, I dare not judge ſo rigorouſly; the</hi> 5. <hi>of</hi> Heb. 2. <hi>comes near my heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We wiſh other Scriptures did alſo, that concern his duty in this caſe: 'Tis true, Jeſus Chriſt can have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on the ignorant, and ſuch as are out of the way, as that <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. ſpeaketh; But then he teacheth them, gives his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to them, and brings them into the way, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22, 23. We allow his diſtinction of ignorance, and that to the weakly ignorant inſtruction is to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but how much affected obſtinate ignorance is to be found with ſuch as ruſh upon Sacraments? And to admit
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:119878:87"/>ſuch was farre from Chriſts minde in that Scripture, being to encourage poor ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant ſouls to come to be taught by him, and after to tender themſelves to Sacraments, and to be encouraged to do ſo.</p>
               <p>Further he ſaith, <hi>For the ſcandalous we know there muſt be admonition firſt twice or thrice,</hi> Mat. 18.15, 16. <hi>and then if they continue obſtinate, to be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why is not this courſe taken? If it ought to be, why is not the beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient uſed for ſuch an order? And if this <hi>ought to be,</hi> how will Free Admiſſion of all without exception (ſeeing this Ordinance, as he ſaith, is converting) ſtand with his Excommunication? Should any be kept from converting Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances?</p>
               <p>But, ſaith he, <hi>I cannot finde that this Excommunication is in reference meerly to this Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Granted; There are other ends, but your <hi>meerly</hi> implies this is one, <hi>viz.</hi> to keep ſcandalous perſons from the Sacrament; If from Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in general, as you ſpeak, then from the choiceſt part of it, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:119878:88"/>in the Communion of Saints in this Ordinance.</p>
               <p>The laſt Objection he undertakes to anſwer, is raiſed <hi>from the Texts that are alleadged for a ſeparation from wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To theſe he anſwers, firſt in the general, <hi>That there ought to be a ſeparation from the ſins and evil courſes of wicked men, and from their common familiarity, but not from the Sacrament, unleſſe in caſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this we Anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to a particular perſon, ſuppoſe I am of ſuch a Congregation (and that too only by habitation, never by any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe joyning in ſuch a communion) where ſuch corruptions do abound, that it is even impoſſible for men to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all, or if I tell it to the Miniſter or Church, I ſhall be reproached for it, (as we need not travell farre to finde ſuch caſes) and I have with great patience waited for <hi>Reformation</hi> and a <hi>Church-Eſtabliſhment</hi> according to God, what obligation is upon me from God or man, but that I may ſeparate from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, for the eaſe and comfort of my own Conſcience?</p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:119878:88"/>
               <p n="2">2. What if a Congregation be ſo lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vend with cuſtomary ignorance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, and ſcoffing at holineſſe (as 'tis too too eaſie to finde ſuch, nay where may one finde better in the ſtate they are now in) and a godly Preacher comes to this people, and a few godly own him; Muſt this Preacher and few godly be enforced to communicate with ſuch (after due means uſed for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the reſt) or may they not withdraw from the reſt who are ſcoffers at godlineſs? ſure we beleeve God and Angels, and Saints will juſtifie ſuch a ſeparation in this Ordinance, and to draw into a cloſer communion to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe diſcipline among themſelves; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when ſuch a Congregation was never orderly united and joynted toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a free ſubmiſſion to the Goſpel; having in moſt places never enjoy'd it in the power of it, which conſideration, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, wipes off many objections.</p>
               <p>Now to his Scriptures, he firſt ſaith that <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20, 21. are meant only of ſeparation from ſinfull courſes and common familiarity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To that of the <hi>Epheſians, Have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:119878:89"/>darkneſſe, but rather reprove them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore if we muſt not be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with wicked men in a wicked acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>v.</hi> 7. and muſt have <hi>no fellowſhip</hi> with them, then not <hi>Church-fellowſhip,</hi> if I can help it; ſpecially in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Supper, in which a wicked man is converſant, as to himſelf, in an <hi>unfruitfull work;</hi> and if I by my parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with him encourage him (as I do) I have fellowſhip with a wicked man in an unfruitfull work of his, ſpecially if I do not reprove him. Can M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> conceive, that <hi>Paul</hi> forbidding any fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with wicked men, gave them an allowance to let them profane the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with them? It founds harſh and incongruous.</p>
               <p>To that of the 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 10.21, 22. <hi>I would not ye ſhould have fellowſhip with devils, ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Grant it, <hi>Paul</hi> reproves their eating at Idol feaſts, as hath been ſhewed, yet if wicked men come to the Lords Supper in a profane manner, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves to be but of Satans king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and preſently after receiving, they return to Satans worſhip in ſports and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:119878:89"/>playes, and abetted profanneſs, ſure it is juſtifiable for ſuch as fear God to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from them, ſpecially when they long reſiſt and ſcoff at the power of the word; and if the godly continue to communicate with ſuch, 'tis little better then fellowſhip with devils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſame may be ſaid of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. Though the wife is to abide with her husband, it doth not follow but that ſhe may ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from him as to Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>He conceives three more Scriptures may, <hi>haply,</hi> as he ſpeaks, he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood only of ſeparating from mens evil courſes; he ſaith but <hi>haply,</hi> firſt as to <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.19. <hi>If thou return, then will I bring thee again, and thou ſhalt ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me; and if thou take forth the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my mouth: let them return unto thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We aſſert this is meant of Church-Reformation, and not only of ſeparating from ſinfull courſes in their lives. <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> was ſent to convince, preach down, and reform publique abuſes in Gods worſhip; The wicked ſcorned and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him, therefore <hi>Jeremiah</hi> (as every zealous Preacher ought) was
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:119878:90"/>commanded to be as Gods mouth unto them, and thoſe he did convert he was to ſeparate them as the <hi>precious from the vile;</hi> which very fully points at and warrants ſuch a ſeparation we plead for: For any to ſay, that the precious is meant of words or things, and not of perſons, is very weak; for the Lord ſaith, Let <hi>them</hi> return, which muſt be meant of perſons.</p>
               <p>The next of 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Withdraw from every brother that walketh diſorderly, &amp;c.</hi> is alſo meant of withdrawing as to Church-Communion, as is clear by the following words: At <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and exhorts the diſorderly: At the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, he exhorteth the Church, that if ſuch diſorderly perſons will not obey, then the Church is to have no company with them, that they may be aſhamed; which Learned men generally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand as to Church-ſociety: Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating or withdrawing being both for that end, as one, that the diſorderly perſon may be aſhamed and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So of <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.6. The hating of the deeds of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> no queſtion implies, ſeparation from them in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion:
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:119878:90"/>Sure M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> will not allow Chriſtianity and their hereſies to conſiſt.</p>
               <p>There are other Scriptures which he ſaith do only reſpect common familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not a ſeparation as to Church-Communion.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with fornicators,</hi> &amp;c. which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freys</hi> will have to be only of common familiarity, not as to Church-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>No? Muſt not known fornicatours (for of ſuch it muſt be meant) be caſt out of the Church, if they continue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate? Who then muſt be caſt out? The ſame rule he gives of Covetous, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, Railers, Drunkards, Extortio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; where the force of the argument, as Learned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Dickson</hi> on the place well obſerves, is this; <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaith he, had wrot to them before, not to keep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, nor to eat with ſuch (which ſtrongly implies their <hi>non</hi>-communion) therefore much more ought they to caſt out from among themſelves that inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon, which is the caſe he argues: Now how many <hi>covetous, drunkards, revilers</hi> and <hi>extortioners</hi> are to be found
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:119878:91"/>in moſt Congregations, <hi>open revilers</hi> of the Preacher, if godly and zealous, and of the godly; to which may be added many other ſinnes of as high a nature: Now ſuppoſe the greater party ſhall be ſuch (as it may eaſily be ſuppoſed in moſt Congregations) who ſhall Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate them? being ſeveral hundreds in ſome places? 'Twere a vain thing to undertake it; therefore the leſſer party muſt withdraw, and labour to draw others after them, or elſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles command muſt utterly be waved.</p>
               <p>That of 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.14. hath been open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: As to <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. of avoiding ſuch as make diviſions: 'Tis clear, as moſt Interpreters, for exerciſing Diſcipline on them; To avoid a man, is to look upon him as caſt out.</p>
               <p>The ſame may be ſaid, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cotton</hi> ſtrongly argues from that Scripture, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>From ſuch turn away,</hi> which no queſtion points at <hi>non</hi>-communion, for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> himſelf will ſure allow, that the ſins enumerated in the former verſes, deſerve it.</p>
               <p>So of <hi>John</hi> 2.10, 11. Sure he will not have ſuch as deny the doctrine of Chriſt to be continued in the Church, and come
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:119878:91"/>to Sacraments, for of ſuch <hi>John</hi> there ſpeaks.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.24, 25. viz. <hi>Make no friendſhip with an angry man,</hi> &amp;c. We finde not uſually preſſed in this caſe; and yet a furious man (as the wiſe man there cals him) is not fit to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſts family; if it appear reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly upon him, and cauſe him to break out into other ſins, as uſually it doth.</p>
               <p>His laſt is <hi>Titus</hi> 3.10. <hi>Reject an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is this only of common familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty too? Then heretiques muſt alſo it ſeems be continued.</p>
               <p>Now he concludes, <hi>All theſe Scriptures forbid us wicked familiarity in their ſins, not a bare accompanying in Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We acknowledge it in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Ordinances of prayer and preaching, but not in Sacraments, and in full Church-Communion; The truth is, tis a ridiculous thing to conceive that the Apoſtle ſhould command <hi>not to keep company with, to avoid, to turn away from, to reject</hi> ſuch as are rightfully (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfrays</hi> would prove) continued in
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:119878:92"/>the fellowſhip of the Church; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Apoſtle would fully contradict himſelf in other Scriptures, if he ſhould, where he bids all the members <hi>have the ſame care one of another,</hi> 1. Cor. 12.25. <hi>To love as Brethren, To be as one brotherhood,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17. <hi>To exhort; To comfort one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,</hi> which implies all ſweet and open familiarity together; Now how can this be if they muſt <hi>reject, turn from, keep no company one with another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next he anticipates the uſuall anſwer to his Argument, <hi>viz. If I muſt decline a wicked man, ſo as not to eat with them (which I interpret by our ordinary conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation) how much more muſt I decline him at this Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He anſwers, <hi>'Tis a fallacy, and is ſorry to ſee many gravel'd at it; I muſt not be ſuch a mans common companion, therefore I must not go to Church with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This ſerves but to gratifie the ignorance and ſuperſtition of too many, who think it enough if <hi>they come to Church;</hi> We muſt all, ſay they, go to Church, and have the Communion at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> He's worſe then a Jew that will not; And too many know little further what true Church-Communion is.</p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:119878:92"/>
               <p>But ſaith he, <hi>Arguments from the leſſe to the greater muſt be in things of the ſame kinde and nature; which theſe are not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sir, Common familiarity is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to Church-members, as hath been ſhewed, and forbidden to others; upon weighty Grounds; for how can there be mutuall edification without fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar coming together, which though the means may be ſometime in eating and drinking together, yet the people of the Lord do, or ſhould do all to the praiſe of God and their mutuall comfort in him whenever they meet; and ſo 'tis a degree of Church-communion.</p>
               <p>Yea (ſaith he) <hi>Eating with another is in my own arbitration; I muſt not chooſe evil, but I am bound to go to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> True, In Gods way, but not to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of other mens ſins, which I do, if I do not my duty to prevent them; which as the caſe ſtands in the moſt Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is hard to do, as hath been ſhewed.</p>
               <p>He ſaith, <hi>He underſtands</hi> Mat. 18.17. <hi>in the third ſenſe,</hi> which is, <hi>That there ought to be no ſeparation from any in any of Gods Ordinances, unleſſe in caſe of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and ſo</hi> 1 Cor. 5.1.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:119878:93"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Yea Sir, It may reach to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>excommunicable,</hi> when the Officers ſhall neglect their duty. We require any Scripture to ſhew an obligation upon a Church-member to abide in ſuch a Church-communion where no hope of redreſſe of ſuch abuſes, it may be the whole leavened.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If Excommunication ought to be, why do not godly men when they have power from God and man put it in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe? If the Parochiall frames as mixt, be too corrupt to take it up of themſelves, by reaſon of an averſeneſſe to any ſuch Reformation; it will ſurely juſtifie the godly and willing people in <hi>non</hi>-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though in <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. There be no mention of the Sacrament, yet that one end of Church-cenſures is to keep the viſibly-unworthy from it, is confeſſed by himſelf in <hi>p.</hi> 84. as hath been obſerved: He further urgeth ſeverall Scriptures which prove <hi>non</hi>-communion with the wicked, which he ſaith <hi>are to be underſtood only in caſe of Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and are many leagues off from the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of the Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let it be granted, that theſe
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:119878:93"/>Scriptures are to be underſtood in caſe of Excommunication; But thoſe Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures do ſuppoſe it to be exercis'd in all Churches, as in the Primitive Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es it was; We ſtill ſay to you and others, that the caſe is far different, where peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have for the moſt part owned the profeſſion of Chriſtianity from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Laws, and not from the Goſpel powerfully preached, and do ſtill abide in bitter enmity to the power of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and too many as great revilers of it, as Papiſts or flat Atheiſts; And had never diſcipline exerciſed, nor did ever ſubject to it, and being now call'd upon to do it, do hate and ſcorn it, and ſuch who are willing to doe it; as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> well obſerves in his ſerious Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>p.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>Now he concludes with 4. wiſhes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That we had a Government eſtabliſht in the Church, the neareſt in Christian pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that may be to the Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ,</hi> Yea, let him ſay, That which the Word of God holds forth; Jeſus Chriſt did not ſo little conſider of the rule and order of his Churches, as to leave it wholly to Chriſtian Prudence, which is the very inlet of all tyranny that hath
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:119878:94"/>been exerciſed over the Churches of God: yet we allow Chriſtian prudence, if clearly according to generall rules of the Word of God.</p>
               <p>But he would have it <hi>eſtabliſht:</hi> By whom? We preſume he means the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate; What, cannot the Goſpel do it? Sure Jeſus Chriſt would rule by the <hi>rod of his mouth,</hi> Iſa. 11.4. <hi>the rod of his ſtrength,</hi> Pſal. 110.2, 3. And not by Magiſtrates compelling Edicts: Though in bringing all to converting Ordinances, we humbly conceive their power is to be put forth, and in reſtraining blaſphemies, but not to the whole order of Church-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; let the Goſpel be left to its proper work; If men ſpeak of countenancing by their power; what would we have more then protection in our duties, which bleſſed be God, we enjoy; The Lord free the Spirits of godly men who pleade for <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>diſcipline,</hi> from this ſnare; for we dare averre it to be a great one.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He wiſheth, <hi>That the duty of fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall correption, a watching over, and admoniſhing one another in love, were better known and practiſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let him wiſh and pray for it
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:119878:94"/>more; But this may be preſt by a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter till his heart ake, conſidering the cuſtomary formality the moſt are held under, and ſtand for nothing, and will not reach any reall Reformation, till they ſhall be cal'd upon, to come and profeſſe their willingneſſe to ſubmit to ſuch diſcipline actively and paſſively: An then M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humphreys</hi> and others will diſcern the temper of this generation as they yet remain; That they will neither enter in themſelves, nor ſuffer others to do ſo:</p>
               <p n="3">3. He wiſheth, <hi>That men would look more into their own conſciences, and leave the judging of others ſpirits, hearts, and reins alone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Who he means in this admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we know not; we know not of any who undertake this kinde of judging, but judge by <hi>profeſſion</hi> and <hi>converſation;</hi> We mean godly Miniſters, who call upon their people to ſubmit to diſcipline, and joynt communion; We wiſh M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humphreys</hi> ſeriouſly to conſider whether he need not take this back again to his own ſpirit; For his bringing the practiſe of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation under the doom of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Phariſaiſm;</hi> as hath been obſerved:
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:119878:95"/>And as he cals for ſo univerſall a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we wiſh he extend it not beyond what his own conſcience may one day fly in in his face for; for countenancing igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and prophane ſouls in their waies, as his piece ſerves for nothing elſe: Oh ſay they, let us go on, for all what our Miniſter ſaith, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humphreys</hi> in his Book ſaith, <hi>they ought to judge charitably of me, though we refuſe to profeſſe Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Faith, and to come under diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> and checks theſe new troubleſome Miniſters for it; And we all ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>Sir, We are bold to minde you again that you have deeply wounded the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of many of your brethren, and the Lords people in the Nation, and made the wicked bold in their wickedneſſe, and have much hardned them againſt their Miniſters, See <hi>Eze.</hi> 13.22, 23.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, He wiſheth, <hi>That though there may be ſome judging by the fruits, yet hat wiſe religious men would be more cautious of countenancing theſe Separations in the viſible Church, becauſe upon this ſcore he ſaith there may be Separation upon Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſame Church,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If he mean by Separations and gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:119878:95"/>of Churches, the practiſe which we have in this Treatiſe laboured to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, <hi>viz.</hi> That when a faithfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Goſpel is ſent to an ignorant, ſuperſtitious, prophane people, (the moſt part by far ſuch:) And if it pleaſe the Lord to work upon a part of this people, as to draw them out to own the Goſpel from him, and to conform to it, and ſo that Preacher draweth the willing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon their profeſſion, into a more cloſe union and fellowſhip together, waiting and labouring to bring on the reſt to them; If we ſay he mean by this, the ſeparation he would caution againſt, we hope and pray that wiſe and religious men will not be deterred from it by any thing M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humphreys</hi> hath produced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, but will in the ſtrength of the Lord ſet about it againſt all oppoſitions, All conſiderations of eaſe or intereſt being thrown off: By which means, 1. They will be found faithfull Stewards to their Maſter. 2. They will keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves pure, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. 3. They will ſanctifie the Name of Chriſt aright in this Ordinance of the Supper. 4. They will be free from the ſinne of flattering ſouls to hell by it. 5. They ſhall diſcern
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:119878:96"/>how the Lord owneth and bleſſeth their Miniſtery. 6. They ſhall have ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Saints. 7. They will by this provoke and awake all to examine their condition. 8. They will act ſutably to thoſe rich and glorious promiſes of the building of the Lords Temple in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daies of the Goſpel, <hi>Zech.</hi> 6.12, 13. and many others.</p>
               <p>For Separations in the viſible Church which he ſuggeſts dangerous, We an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That if as much and great profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and abominations ſhall be fouled with the viſible Church (as is too ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent) as even among ſuch know not God, Then Separations as to the holy things of God, where holy men have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly right, is juſtifiable in the eyes of God, Saints and Angels.</p>
               <p>For his ſuggeſted danger of ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon ſeparation; 1. We anſwer, That how is there <hi>properly</hi> a Separation, when there hath been no true uniting, nor hath one perſon conſidered himſelf to have any more relation to another, then as one of their Pariſh, but hear one another lie, ſwear, and commit together, and rather encourage then reprove one another for it; Separation is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:119878:96"/>in and from a true Church-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and not from ungodlineſſe and prophaneſſe in a Scripture ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, what if there may be unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſouls ſeparate from ſuch a joynt-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion (as 'tis like there may in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt conſtitutions) ſhall there, for that reaſon, be no Church-communion nor endeavour after it?</p>
               <p>What if Excommunication be ſet up by a Law from men in every Pariſh, (which we beleeve to be impoſſible to any purpoſe, as the caſe ſtands with moſt Miniſters and People who are bitterly againſt it) and there ſhould 50 lyars, ſwearers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be caſt out, would not there lie the ſame Objection againſt this practiſe alſo? And yet the Author makes us beleeve he would have Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſet up.</p>
               <p>Now when M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> hath done all, let us ſee how far we can gather from his own expreſſions an implied allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our own practiſe, though his Book in the main fights againſt it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He cals for Church eſtabliſhment, and for Diſcipline, for watching over one another, for mutuall Reproof and Admonition, and confeſſeth there comes
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:119878:97"/>guilt and defilement upon a ſoul if it be neglected.</p>
               <p>Now we crave of our Brethren of the Miniſtery, and the people we preach to, and others, to conſider, that theſe are the duties we call upon for to be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and that people that fear the Lord might ſubmit conſcionably to the practiſe of them; We crave of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Humfreys</hi> his more candid and honeſt interpretation of other his Brethren acting conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the Lords work, according to the light imparted to him, labouring to extricate the people by the good hand of God with them, out of ignorance, ſinne, and dead-hearted formality, by a reall practiſe and not pretended only of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; And that the Lord may humble him for his great evil in this little but miſchievous piece, ſo miſerably ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the turns of the enemies of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and that he will ſpeedily call it in, or we ſhall pray that the Lord will ſtir up others to do it for him.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:119878:97"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BE pleaſed to take notice, that this Treatiſe hath been above this half Year fitted for the Preſſe, but by reaſon of the death of a friend to whom it was committed to be printed, it hath been retarded.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed alſo to take notice that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Anthony Palmer</hi> hath in the Preſſe ſeverall Sermons on <hi>Matt.</hi> 8.23, 24, 25, 26, 27. Intituled, <hi>The Tempestuous Soul Calmed by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
